<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The thousand years kingdom of Christ, in its full Scripture-state answering Mr. Baxter's new treatise, in opposition to it : humbley presented to the churches of Christ, particularly to the angels of the churches / by T. Beverley, a fore-runner to the everlasting Gospel of that kingdom, near to be preach'd.</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27629</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17894191</idno>
  <idno type="VID">106748</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248553480</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38703</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">17894191</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27629)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106748)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1116:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The thousand years kingdom of Christ, in its full Scripture-state answering Mr. Baxter's new treatise, in opposition to it : humbley presented to the churches of Christ, particularly to the angels of the churches / by T. Beverley, a fore-runner to the everlasting Gospel of that kingdom, near to be preach'd.</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped with loss of imprint; best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Glorious kingdom of Christ.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Millennium --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Second Advent --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106748:1"/>
            <p>THE Thousand Years Kingdom OF CHRIST, IN ITS FULL SCRIPTURE-STATE: Answering Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> New <hi>TREATISE,</hi> In Opposition to It.</p>
            <p>Humbly Presented to the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PARTICULARLY TO THE <hi>Angels of the Churches▪</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>T. BEVERLEY,</hi> A Fore-Runner to the <hi>Everlasting Gospel</hi> of that KINGDOM, Near to be Preach'd.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>REVEL. XIV. 7.</bibl> Fear God, and give Glory to Him, for the Hour of his Judgment, <hi>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Government,</hi> is Come.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106748:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106748:2"/>
            <head>THE ANSWER TO M<seg rend="sup">R</seg>. Baxter's New Treatise, OF THE <hi>Kingdom of Christ, <hi>In Opposition to the Near Approaching di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct</hi>
               </hi> Kingdom <hi>of our</hi> Lord Jesus Christ, <hi>as</hi> That Great Son of Man, <hi>for a Thousand Years: By me Asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE True way of Answering, and so of defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Books, is in my esteem That; which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the least Reflexion on Persons, Any Catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing▪ at Expressions, that may seem doubtful, and Surmising some strange opinions in Reserve under Them, which the Author makes no open Profession of; or Finding out the Smaller <hi>Foiblees,</hi> or Fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lures of speech, which signifie little in the main Pursuit of Truth, that ought to be every ones Aim. For who so speaks, as with the <hi>Tongue of Angels,</hi> as not to darken <hi>Counsel,</hi> even as<note place="margin">Job. 38. 2</note>
               <hi>Job,</hi> though Right in the Main, by <hi>Words without Knowledge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is best therefore on both sides to proceed to the very merit of Things; Frankly and Immediately to own what is, and to disown what is not ones Sense, and so to Attack or defend; and to let All Circumstances Attend the main Chance, as those who strive not for the Mastery of little
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106748:3"/> Concernment, but to Receive Greater Judgment; Wasting both Time, and Increasing the Expense of the Press, and not Attaining True Sense and Knowledge, which is every ones chief Interest.</p>
            <p>There are also within All Grand Points, outlying Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Search and Enquiry; As appears even in the chief <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith,</hi> wherein All difficulties cannot be with Clearness, or Certainty Resolv'd; especially in this Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphere, this Gloomy State of Understanding, wherein we are; Under that double <hi>Apostasie,</hi> in which we now Grope, even as the Blind; the <hi>Apostasie</hi> of Humane nature, taking away the Glory of our First Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation, and the <hi>Apostasie</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> that hath so Eclips'd the Restitution design'd us by the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> until the 1260 <hi>Days</hi> of that <hi>Apostasie</hi> are Expir'd, (which as I Account shall be at 97.) Then the Light will be more, and more Precious or Clear, until the <hi>Bright Day</hi> of the 1000<note place="margin">Zech. 14. 6. 7.</note>
               <hi>Years Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore the main Pillars of any Point, can be Found to stand Firm, we must, as yet, be Content to be in doubt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning many Particularities: And He that can Vindicate the Principals, may be excus'd, if when Conveniencies, and Advantages of doing the other, serve Him not; He pass over many such, in his defence of what He hath Asserted, when He is Encounter'd.</p>
            <p>Now that which in my Judgment, I would elect and desire to do in these Fornam'd Things, I am under a necessity to do; Having a person to Treat with, whom I always Sincerely Lov'd and Honour'd; and I am perswaded nothing can, or shall Remove me from it; One, to whom God hath (especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in all <hi>Practical Knowledge</hi>) Given <hi>Five Talents,</hi> and He hath made them <hi>Ten;</hi> and shall, I am humbly Confident, be <hi>Ruler over Ten Cities</hi> in that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which It is not yet Given to him to see. I am Bound therefore to Omit any passages wherein he may seem severe, For his very Reproofs to me are an Excellent Oyl.</p>
            <p>My own Abasing Circumstances oblige me also to all the Modesty, and Awe of Insinuating the least of Diminution on any Person, much more towards one, to whom I Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my self on many Accounts oblig'd, and so I ever shall.</p>
            <p>Lastly, The Charge of Printing Binds me to all the Fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Providence, both as to Paper, and the Labour of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106748:3"/> Press, that I can, and Admonishes me to speak the most I can to the purpose in Little; So that though I do not make my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer in Great as I would do, yet I hope it will be Accepted.</p>
            <p>There are some Things yet, that I would give Account of in Relation to my own General Sentiments, that may be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to premise, but that would not be Considerable to be taken notice of, but as They may make, what I have further to say, more Acceptable, the Prejudices thence Arising, being Remov'd thereby.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whereas I am suppos'd a Person, so Swoln with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of <hi>Prophecying,</hi> that I would not be willing to Read a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of My Self; I do declare I am no <hi>Enthusiast,</hi> nor pretend to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> but by Interpretation of <hi>Scripture Prophecy;</hi> which yet, if Rightly interpreted, I Affirm <hi>It is the Spirit of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> because it is the Testimony of <hi>Jesus;</hi> But every one hath the same Right to Search, and to Judge, that I dare pretend to, who will Separate himself through Desire to Inter-med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with this Wisdom. I am I humbly Acknowledge to the Free Grace of God Assur'd, I have a True Scheme of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Prophecy</hi> in all main parts, Relating to the <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> Assur'd, I mean, by such a <hi>Symmetry,</hi> and Agreement of Scripture, with undoubted <hi>History,</hi> and Matter of Fact, and so am fully satisfied, I shall not be mistaken in that Great 97. This notwithstanding, I Avow to all the World, I have been always, since I set my mind to these Enquiries, most Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive after all Contrary, or differing Apprehensions, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my small Compass I could Reach, and to An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wer Them, especially to my self, as a most Rigorous Exacter of my own Satisfaction concerning all Objections; And I caa truly say, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, <hi>Out of the Eater hath come forth Meat,</hi> and <hi>Sweetness out of the Strong,</hi> I mean out of the knottiest Objections, Confirmation.</p>
            <p>And as I have diligently Read, and weighed the Arguings of the Reverend, and Penetrating Objecter I now deal with; So I Give him my most unfeigned Thanks for the pains He hath therein Taken, and do Acknowledge many of his Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections very close, and to the purpose, and that it is no other then I ought to expect, having seriously desir'd All to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince me of Error; especially the Pastors and Doctors of the Evangelical Ministery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas the Note of <hi>Conformity</hi> is oft Imprinted upon me; (I do not believe it with any unkind Intention, but to press
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106748:4"/> me the closer in Reasoning.) I do acknowledge, I have been of the not only most Moderate, but Wary and Abstemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Consormists,</hi> and that from my most native sense of Things in Religion: But since I have seen into <hi>Prophecy,</hi> I have still made the most Modest and Silent Recesses I could from <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> as seeing the Regimental and Synagogal <hi>Constitution</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> as it is distinguishingly, (but ought not so to be) stiled, to be under <hi>Prophetic Censure,</hi> as I have with all the Caution I could, yet Freely declar'd in the <hi>Reformation to be Reform'd;</hi> wherein I do indeed Deny the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or as we speak <hi>Clergy,</hi> to be peculiar; yet I acknowledge a <hi>Gospel-Eldership</hi> and <hi>Doctorate</hi> withal my Heart.</p>
            <p>This I declare with all <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>godly Fear,</hi> and Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting to many, very many Excelling Persons of the Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity (with whom I confess my Self altogether Unworthy to be Nam'd, or once Thought of) All that is Due.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The boldness of the Censure of <hi>Dissenters</hi> from the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> as <hi>Semi-Sadduces</hi> of the <hi>Apostacy,</hi> I humbly Remonstrate to in these Particulars:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That as it stands in the <hi>Title-page</hi> of the Reverend Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jector's Book, especially with the several Times mention of me, as a <hi>Conformist,</hi> I fear the <hi>Auth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi>'s Sense may by some unwarily be mistaken, as if I Branded the Body of Those, so generally call'd <hi>Dissenters.</hi> But the Book so clears that; I hope it will not be mistaken by Any, seeing there can be no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son I should so charge Them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I do solemnly declare, I Abhor so slanderous a Charge upon any persons whatever, holding the <hi>Resurrection</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> speaking only in the Abstract, <hi>viz.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Semi-Sadducism if the Apostacy:</hi> And I think the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference very Great; we are all in <hi>Adam's Apostacy,</hi> I do not think it fit therefore to call any person on that account <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postate;</hi> much of the <hi>Antichristian Apostacy,</hi> I have great Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to fear, is upon us All, should therefore All be call'd <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristians</hi> or <hi>Apostates!</hi> I do affirm, the Enmity to the <hi>Doctrine of the Kingdom of Christ</hi> is Antichristian Semi-Sadducism, (ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king both in the Abstract) having set up that in <hi>Kingdom</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit; God forbid▪ I should attribute this in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete to any, especially <hi>Protestant.</hi> And if the One cannot be separated from the Other, I do most Humbly, with beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Pardon of All, <hi>Recall, Retract,</hi> and <hi>Recant</hi> that word.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106748:4"/>3. I do boldly Avouch, the Reason of that Great Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, of the Great Contradiction, the Great Dis-inclination coneerning, and to this Great Doctrine of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> is, that the Sable Wings of the <hi>Antichristian Apostacy</hi> Hover over the <hi>Christian Profession,</hi> and as that began to Rise, so that Doctrine hath been growing under Disrepute till it was out of all Honour, but hath gradually Recover'd since the Reformation, and is Recovering, and will be in its Glory at the end of the <hi>Apostacy. viz.</hi> at, and from 1697.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I do most Humbly, but most Sincerely Appeal to God, I am not only Free from, but have a great Antipathy and Reluctancy, and even Horrour at those kind of Notions: The Reverend <hi>Objector</hi> makes common to me and Dr. <hi>Moor,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Turner;</hi> how they Explain them I have not so much as Applied my self to know; I even fly from those Notions of the <hi>Eternal Words</hi> uniting it self to the <hi>Prime Being,</hi> or to the <hi>Ʋnixersal Soul</hi> of the <hi>Creation,</hi> mention'd <hi>p.</hi> 2. Or of <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Life, Ʋniversal Matter, Ʋniversal Body,</hi> mention'd <hi>p. 25. &amp;c.</hi> Looking upon them as vain Philosophy, and resting wholly in <hi>Scripture Expressions,</hi> concerning all things of this Nature, and the <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>Athanasian</hi> Explanations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Great <hi>Mediator's Person.</hi> I dare not once think of any <hi>Worlds</hi> before that, the <hi>Scripture, Genes.</hi> 1. gives us the <hi>History</hi> of the <hi>Creation</hi> of; Nor after the <hi>Kingdom delivered up;</hi> or any whatever, whereof the <hi>Eternal Word made Man,</hi> and according to the <hi>Flesh,</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>David</hi> is not <hi>the Head of;</hi> least the Great <hi>Analogy of Faith</hi> be Injur'd: I know no Expressions in the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> concerning <hi>Transubstantiation</hi> signifying any more than an <hi>Eternal</hi> and <hi>Ʋbiquitary Vertue</hi> of the <hi>Sacrifice of Christ,</hi> as Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd and Applied by the <hi>Eternal Spirit.</hi> Nor have I the least Approbation of Dr. <hi>Moore's Aiery Tryal;</hi> nor Mr. <hi>Medes</hi> Thoughts, that we shall not be sure of our Salvation till the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> any further than as the <hi>Apostle Peter</hi> says, The <hi>Time of Restitution</hi> will be the Illustrious and publick <hi>Blotting out of Sin.</hi> I use no cloudy nor misty Expressions with an Intention to hide any such suspected <hi>Doctrines,</hi> but own my self of the Faith and Judgment of the most sound <hi>Orthodox Protestant Divines,</hi> and more especially Those who are call'd <hi>Calvinists,</hi> although I make them no Standard of Faith, but as they agree with the Word of God; I do En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106748:5"/> Love and Delight in all the Holy <hi>practical</hi> Discourses of <hi>Protestants,</hi> especially <hi>English Preachers</hi> of the <hi>Gospel?</hi> and more especially of Those (however called <hi>Puritants,</hi> or now <hi>Dissenters</hi>) even All alike, who come nearest to the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> in <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Prayer:</hi> Amongst whom I have a Singular Esteem for many Writings of the to Me truly Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable <hi>Objector.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Value I have for Dr. <hi>Crispe,</hi> is, Because I think God gave him an Extraordinary <hi>Talent</hi> in Setting out the <hi>Ʋnsearchable Riches of Christ;</hi> but do not <hi>Jurare in verba,</hi> tye my self to his Words or Phrases, or Sentiments in All Things; but am very clear He intended not any Dis-obligation, but highest Obligation to Holiness; and Comparing all Parts of Him together, am very well perswaded, He was <hi>Sound in the Faith,</hi> and of Excellent Ministerial Accomplishments; however if in some Parts divided from the rest, he may seem unwary: And in one Particular place, <hi>pag. 346. of the last E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> He so allows the order of <hi>Calling, Conversion, Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> as shews it is a differing manner of Apprehending Things as in the <hi>Eternity of God,</hi> and in the Actual <hi>Ransom</hi> for Sin paid by Christ, and not as He works in us; that gave him the Reasons of speaking of <hi>Justification,</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> from <hi>Eternity;</hi> and before <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I understand my self no otherwise to have spoken of <hi>Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> by the <hi>Essential Righteousness of God,</hi> than as the <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings</hi> and <hi>Obedience of Christ,</hi> by which we are <hi>Justified,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Value from the <hi>Infinite Righteousness</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Word;</hi> to which all Scripture agrees, calling it the <hi>Righteousness of God, and Christ;</hi> Jehovah <hi>our Righteousness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, I know my self to agree Substantially in These Things with the Soundest <hi>Ministers</hi> of the <hi>Word;</hi> however we may seemingly differ in our manner of Explanation. And so I am fully satisfied Dr. <hi>Crisp</hi> did.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whereas there is Doubt made, Whether I Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the <hi>Kingdum of Christ</hi> to have been a Kingdom all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the <hi>Thousand Years:</hi> I do now Fully and Freely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Christ to have on his <hi>Head many Crowns;</hi> I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the <hi>Man Christ Jesus</hi> by his Union to the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> is a King without <hi>Beginning</hi> or <hi>End of Days;</hi> Even by that which we call a <hi>Communication of Properties:</hi> He is a <hi>King</hi> from <hi>Eternity</hi> to <hi>Eternity,</hi> as the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> is, even in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106748:5"/> State of the <hi>Kingdom delivered up to God,</hi> and <hi>to the Father, All in All;</hi> And that our <hi>Eternal</hi> Enjoyment of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Ʋnion</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> with <hi>Him</hi> is by the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> in <hi>Our Nature.</hi> And that <hi>This</hi> is that <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Acknowledge further, That the Government of God in the World, and especially towards his Church, was by the <hi>Eternal Word;</hi> as to be <hi>Incarnate;</hi> and still the <hi>Manifestation</hi> hereof was Higher and Higher; the <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Prophecy</hi> clearer, as his <hi>Appearance</hi> in <hi>Flesh</hi> drew nearer; so higher at his <hi>Incarnation,</hi> at his <hi>Baptism,</hi> higher at his <hi>Resurrection</hi> and <hi>Ascension;</hi> when in that Great Scene He received the <hi>Sealed Book</hi> as a <hi>Lamb newly slain,</hi> Rev. 5.</p>
            <p>I Acknowledge further yet an Illustrious Appearing and Breaking out of that <hi>Kingdom</hi> in the <hi>Roman Pagan Empire</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming <hi>Christian,</hi> call'd <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. the <hi>Kingdom of our God;</hi> and that at the <hi>Reformation,</hi> Christ set as it were his <hi>Right Foot on the Sea,</hi> and his <hi>Left Foot on the Earth,</hi> making a Challenge of an <hi>Ʋniversal Dominion</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> Rev. 10.</p>
            <p>But I say, This Kingdom hath been hither to all along Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred by the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> Ruling and Governing, as in the Name of himself as <hi>Son of Man,</hi> and since his Death; as styl'd the <hi>Lamb,</hi> and that it hath been Executed by a <hi>Divine Power</hi> in a Providential Sway of the World, and of all Things in it; and by his Spirit, and his word in an Evangelical and Spiritual Government on his Saints, and by <hi>Judiciary</hi> Acts of Leaving his Enemies to Themselves, to Hardness and Blindness of Heart; As also that the Judgment upon <hi>Spirits</hi> separated from Bodies, is Administred by Christ, Receiving the <hi>Spirits</hi> of his Saints to himself, and Condemning the Wicked to Remain <hi>Spirits</hi> in Prison to the Judgment of the <hi>Great Day</hi> when an Immediate Raising and Condemnation will Fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, even a Being slain or condemn'd with the Sword of Christ's Mouth, and their Carcases seen a 1000 <hi>Years,</hi> and they shall not Live after the 1000 <hi>Years,</hi> but be Cast into the <hi>Lake:</hi> Thus All Judgment is <hi>Committed to the Son,</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> see it, and Lost <hi>Spirits</hi> Believe and Tremble at it.</p>
            <p>Further I Acknowledge, That even when the Kingdom is said to be deliver'd up, and the <hi>Son to be subject,</hi> and God and the Father to be <hi>All in All;</hi> Yet even then, God will, as the Worthy Opposer also Intimates, Govern that Kingdom by the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> Shining out with the <hi>Fathers Glory</hi> in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106748:6"/>
               <hi>Humane Nature</hi> to the Saints by Him united to the <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this I have heretofore made Confession in many Expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, and most particularly in the Treatise, Entituled, <hi>The Kingdom of Christ Entring its Succession in</hi> 97. Page 8.</p>
            <p>I further Acknowledge It cannot be otherwise in any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but that the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>VVord,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which <hi>Three One</hi> are the <hi>Kingternal, Immertal, Invisible,</hi> the <hi>Only wise God,</hi> must be <hi>All in All,</hi> in True and Strict Sense, and that in the same True and Strict Sense, the <hi>Son</hi> as <hi>man, is always subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly I Acknowledge, That together with some Kingdom of Christ, Then shall be a <hi>New Heaven</hi> and a <hi>New Earth,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Righteousness shall dwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far my <hi>Reverend Opponant</hi> and my Self are, so far, as I can Understand and Hope, perfectly Agreed concerning the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> and that we both agree with the <hi>Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now I must come to the Things wherein I must make Confession I am at a very Great but most Unwilling Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance from him; and though the Distance be not in any Points of Necessity to Salvation, yet such as do so much Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrate the Glory of <hi>Christianity,</hi> the Truth of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> so Rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and immmediately Destructive to <hi>Athism</hi> and <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianism;</hi> so chastising of all <hi>Protestant Formality,</hi> External Pomp, Grandieur, and of the Love of this present State and World, that I stand in humble Amazement, that God hath hid Them from his Servant <hi>Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And they are These Four, wherein we differ:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there is besides all the <hi>Kingly State of Christ,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are Agreed, a distinct <hi>Kingdom</hi> to Jesus Christ, as that Great <hi>Son of Man;</hi> To the highest Noontide Glory, of which God hath Assign'd a <hi>Thousand Years;</hi> and when it hath ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erly <hi>Subdued</hi> All <hi>Enemies,</hi> it is to be <hi>deliver'd up to God and the Father,</hi> and the <hi>Son</hi> to be <hi>subject</hi> in that very Sense.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> however it includes, and that very Eminently the Fall of <hi>Pagan Imperial Rome,</hi> yet it is chiefly prepar'd to the destruction of <hi>Antichristian Rome,</hi> in its yet Continuing State, and to set out the Glory that shall follow in <hi>that Kingdom of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth</hi> are not <hi>design'd</hi> to the <hi>Eternal Kingdom of God</hi> by <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> but to this <hi>1000Y. Kingdom of Christ</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. And They <hi>Fly away,</hi> when
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106748:6"/> that <hi>Kingdom</hi> is <hi>deliver'd up,</hi> and the <hi>Wicked</hi> put down into the <hi>Lake,</hi> They being for the Saints above and below.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That there shall be a Glorious Restoration of the <hi>Twelve Tribes of Israel</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> in Answer to All the <hi>Types, Prophesies,</hi> and <hi>Promises;</hi> in <hi>Love to the Fathers,</hi> and as especially to Jesus Christ, <hi>God over All, blessed for ever, who came of Them;</hi> but no such as should either mean a Restoration of the <hi>Levitical Frame,</hi> but in its Spiritual Completion, nor any such <hi>Dominion</hi> of them, as They and some Christians dream of over the <hi>Gentile Christians,</hi> but some Honourary Precedency, while All are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one Body with Them, even the <hi>Israel of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all These, I will endeavour Two Things. First, to establish the Assertions upon so Fundamental Reasons, that though many Particularities can only probably, and not to Satisfaction of those who dissent, be defin'd, yet They must needs perswade the Main Truths. Secondly, I will Answer the most Material Objectious of the <hi>Reverend Opponent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three Things I must also necessarily premise, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Reverend Adversary <hi>Insinuates,</hi> an Adding to the Word of God in Teaching These Things; and <hi>Taking his Name in vain in Prayer for them;</hi> It ought to be consider'd on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side, that there is the same danger in Taking away, that there is in Adding; But on neither side of us, I hope, does such danger lye; For where the word of God is sincerely waited upon, God is no more Severe upon his Servants, then upon <hi>Nathans</hi> mistake in Encouraging <hi>David</hi> to Build the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> but will Reveal in his Time, (at their Being with Christ, if not sooner, when They shall Hear all the <hi>Ʋnutterable My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries,</hi> much more whatever may now be utter'd,) even that unto Them. And as to their Prayers, The <hi>Spirit</hi> Helps <hi>their Infirmities,</hi> even when They Know not what to Pray for, as they ought; and <hi>makes Intercession according to the Will of God for Them,</hi> with <hi>Groans,</hi> that <hi>are not to be Ʋtter'd;</hi> And <hi>God who searcheth the Heart,</hi> Knows the Main Sense of the Mind of his Saints, to be the Mind of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which is always according <hi>to the Will of God.</hi> So They who are so help'd, are Accepted in the Main, though on either side, They may err in particulars.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That which makes the Things pertaining to these points Exceoding difficult to be discours'd, and which lays Those, which discourse of Them, under so Great Prejudice and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106748:7"/> is; Besides the yet continuing Darkness, and Gloomyness cast upon us from the <hi>Apostasie</hi> in the <hi>Atmosphere</hi> or Black Air of which, we yet continue; Besides this, I say, It is a very great difficulty to be Encounter'd, that seeing the Things are in the Wisdom of God, given only, <hi>here a Litte,</hi> and <hi>there a Little,</hi> Men without comparing, and laying Them together, will be subject to stumble concerning them, and without some Scheme of these Things, drawn from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Nay, without a Scheme considerably Full and Large, the Particulars cannot be seen, but at great disadvantage; As the parts of the Body beheld in a Mangled, or Torn Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or some words of the most Excellent Book without their Frame, Concatenation and Coherence; So discourse of the <hi>Symbols of Prophecy</hi> without their Contexture, seems Odd, Antick, Phantastick, Enthusiastick, as the very Images of <hi>Beasts,</hi> Horns, the Whore, that <hi>Prophecy</hi> makes use of; when the High Reason, Spirituality, Admirable Art, wherewith All Things are Couched, and put together, when duly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd, and Fitted out to the other, is not seen, nor conceiv'd.</p>
            <p>And even They, who may have just Apprehensions of some parts of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> if They have not look'd to All parts, may thence Receive Greater Dissatisfaction from the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Judgment of Those, who have consider'd the whole, not only because They do not well Comprehend what is said, that They have not yet understood, and so are displeas'd at that, but much more because Their own Opinions are cross<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and contradicted; This is, when Their Minds are not duly prepared, and Free; But this notwithstanding, I am oblig'd, having laid my Hand to this Plough of the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> not to <hi>Look back;</hi> And I am much Encourag'd, that besides Divine Help, I have Found heretofore very Great Favour, and Candor from my <hi>Reverend Adveasary;</hi> and doubt not, I shall again do so, and from all others in due Time.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I cannot but be aware, that the state of Christians is such; that They seem much unfitted to be Fed with <hi>Ought,</hi> but <hi>Milk;</hi> the Beginnings of the <hi>Doctrine of Christ,</hi> and the First Principles of the <hi>Oracles of God;</hi> and seem else to be Distracted, Puzzled, and Confounded, and not Edified; Also this makes many Holy Good Men, somewhat severe on such discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. But notwithstanding this, saith the <hi>Apostle,</hi> we will go on to Perfection, if God permit: For as in his days, it was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106748:7"/> the only prevention of <hi>Apostasie,</hi> when it was in the <hi>Mystery of Iniquity,</hi> working forward; So it is the Great Instrument, prepar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by God for Recovery out of it, now it is going off; and therefore even on so Great an Account, as the Dissatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of such Good Men, and wherein They Intend well; It is not to be Forborn.</p>
            <p>I come therefore to the first Point propos'd, and that is; That besides the Former most Agreed Representation of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> There is yet a distinct Kingdom, That it is so distinct, as to be often in Scripture spoken of, as <hi>The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Christ,</hi> as in some Respects, the most proper Kingdom of Christ; and his Kingdom, in a most peculiar way; and Christ and the Apostles often speaks of it in such an Eminency; That it is said <hi>to come;</hi> To be <hi>deliver'd up;</hi> and therefore it may be said to Begin, and to end, and it is no injury to the other Representations of his Kingdom before confess'd, and always to be confess'd; And it is a Kingdom so of the Designation, Approbation, and Delight of God and of his Presence in it, and with it, and so much to his Glory; that it is call'd by Christ, also the Kingdom of God, and of his Father, and so also very often in Scripture it is call'd; And to this the <hi>Types,</hi> the <hi>Prophesies</hi> the <hi>Promises,</hi> and Discourses of all kinds in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Writings, have so Great a Regard, that it is the Key of All; and yet in the Admirable Wisdom of God for the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of the <hi>Apostasie</hi> it is least Receiv'd or Believ'd; but as it is either Providentially, or Spiritually, and Evangelically Administred before hand, or as it Issues into Eternity.</p>
            <p>And this Kingdom may be describ'd to be a Supreme Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy or Government, and dispensation of God towards the <hi>Family of Heaven, and Earth</hi> in the Fullness, not only of <hi>Time,</hi> as when Christ First came; but of <hi>Times,</hi> or of All Time; wherein Jesus Christ, as the Great <hi>Son of Man,</hi> or <hi>Lamb</hi> in the Humane Nature, who was First Humbled, and became a Sacrifice by the <hi>Death of the Cross</hi> visibly, as in the Face of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, shall in the very same Nature be so Exalted, Far above Principalities and Powers, and every Name that is named in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and in <hi>Earth,</hi> to the <hi>Glory of God the Father.</hi> And as the Divinity of the Eternal Word, uniting to it self the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, Retir'd its Glory, that that Humane Nature might be in a Humiliation, whereof the Divine was Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely Incapable, and yet in Regard of Personal Union, was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106748:8"/> said to <hi>Empty it self,</hi> and to <hi>Make it self of no Reputation;</hi> even so shall the <hi>Divine Person</hi> so <hi>Oeconomize</hi> and <hi>Model</hi> the <hi>Lustre</hi> of itt <hi>Glory,</hi> that the <hi>Humanity</hi> shall have a <hi>Glory</hi> as Singular to it Self, as the <hi>Humiliation</hi> was; and the <hi>Divinity</hi> of the <hi>Person</hi> of Christ be <hi>Glorified</hi> and <hi>Exalted</hi> in this <hi>Glory;</hi> even as it was <hi>Humbled,</hi> and <hi>became of no Reputation</hi> in the <hi>Humiliation</hi> of the <hi>Humane Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which <hi>Oeconomy</hi> or <hi>Dispensation,</hi> the <hi>Rain-bow</hi> is an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent <hi>Symbol,</hi> whose Glories are received from the Sun, but yet it is obverted to the Sun, and hath its Glory distinct and distant, as in <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Vision, c. 1. From which Vision as shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Glory of the <hi>Throne</hi> of the <hi>Great Son of Man, Ezekiel</hi> is ever after styl'd <hi>Son of man;</hi> so as (except <hi>Daniel</hi> only in a like <hi>Vision</hi> to <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s of the <hi>Sanctuary clean'd</hi>) no other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular person is so nam'd but Christ the True Son of Man. And the <hi>Rain-bow</hi> is ever after made an <hi>Emblem</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom of Christs,</hi> as so receiv'd from the Divinity, and yet so obver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and shining distinctly by it self, that every Eye shall see him.</p>
            <p>In this Kingdom it is, That Jesus Christ as the <hi>Second A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> the <hi>Lord from Heaven,</hi> and <hi>promised Seed</hi> of the <hi>Woman</hi> shall have a <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth,</hi> and a <hi>Restored Creation, Freed</hi> from <hi>Vanity</hi> and <hi>Corruption,</hi> in a perfect Peace of the Creatures, the <hi>Lion</hi> and the <hi>Lamb, &amp;c.</hi> And a <hi>World to come put into his Hand,</hi> with Full Power, and the Serpent and his Seed eating Dust, even all his Enemies at the <hi>Footstool of his Feet,</hi> and so Adorning his Triumph and Glory at the very Beginning of his Reign, and at the End put quite below his Feet into the <hi>Lake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this <hi>Kingdom</hi> it is, that Christ Inhabits the <hi>New Heaven</hi> with all his Saints of the first <hi>Resurrection,</hi> who will then have <hi>Died</hi> and <hi>Slept in</hi> and <hi>by</hi> Him; And then the Glory of Christ shines down and maintains continual Visiits to his <hi>Living Remaining Saints</hi> below as by a <hi>Jacob's Scale</hi> or <hi>Ladder,</hi> who are in the <hi>New Earth</hi> chang'd into <hi>Bodies</hi> of <hi>Paradise</hi> in a <hi>Moment,</hi> and at the same <hi>Moment</hi> in which the Saints Rise.</p>
            <p>Of this <hi>Kingdom</hi> I affirm, it hath a <hi>Thousand Years</hi> dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Glory and full Lustre▪ having besides <hi>Seventy five Years</hi> (from its <hi>Succession</hi>) of <hi>Preparation</hi> for its Glory, before it, and a little Time or Space after this Full G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ory, when its Beams shall be withdrawn from this Lower State; the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of which <hi>Satan</hi> and his <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> all the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106748:8"/>
               <hi>Widked</hi> (that had been Rais'd, to lie at the <hi>Footstool of Christ</hi> from the very Beginning of the Thousand Years, being <hi>Loosed,</hi>) Take to make a bold and insolent Attempt on the <hi>Holy City,</hi> to draw it to Defection, and upon the Appearance of their <hi>Least Abatement</hi> of the former Fervors of Love and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Desire of the Presence of Christ in his <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Kingdom;</hi> Christ that was the Security of his Church in that State, <hi>catches</hi> up his <hi>Saints</hi> to Himself, and to his Throne, and as with <hi>Flames from Heaven,</hi> Throws <hi>Satan</hi> and the <hi>Dead</hi> into the <hi>Lake</hi> of the <hi>second Death</hi> with <hi>Death</hi> it self. And thus the <hi>Last Enemy Death</hi> is subdued; As also by the <hi>Living Saints</hi> putting on <hi>Absolute Incorruption</hi> and <hi>Immortality.</hi> For as <hi>Adam</hi> was to have overcome the Possibility of Death by Obedience, so Christ did indeed by his <hi>Obedience and Death;</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> being <hi>Cast into the Lake,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom is resign'd</hi> up to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Father,</hi> that <hi>He</hi> may be <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Attempt of Satan was by <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> in the <hi>Four Corners of the Earth;</hi> By whom I understand the <hi>Dead,</hi> or the <hi>Lost Wicked,</hi> whose Carkasses are without and abroad: For They go forth to see Them, whose <hi>Worm dieth not,</hi> and their <hi>Fire is not quenched,</hi> and the <hi>Wine-press</hi> is <hi>trodden without the City,</hi> as Places of Execution are <hi>without the Gate,</hi> where they lie Captivated, even as <hi>Satan in the Abyss.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when the Beams of the Glory of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> are withdrawn at the end of the Thousand Years, Both <hi>Satan,</hi> and <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> become <hi>loofed;</hi> and they make the Attempt before spoken of: And it is no more wonder then that Devils Believe and Tremble, and do All they can against God, that they who have seen the Glories of Christ a Thousand Years, should yet rise up against him, when the Chains, those <hi>Spiritual Chains</hi> of the Glory of Christ in his <hi>Kingdom</hi> that were about them, are <hi>loosed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is it any greater Wonder that the <hi>Living Remaining Saints</hi> should be so permitted to Abate in their <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Glory of Christ</hi> then that <hi>Angels</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> in <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise</hi> should Revolt from their Obedience and Loyalty to God; Or that Christ now about to put an end to all Church-state on Earth, should suffer that so just Occasion to do it, as it were <hi>spewing</hi> it out of his <hi>Mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have given a general Delineation of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> and as much as I could in so general a Draught,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106748:9"/> laid my Hand upon the Principal Objections in the <hi>Reverend Adversary</hi>'s Opposition; and now proceed to the Arguments, wherein I must undergo the Disadvantage of being much A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg'd in what I have to Say; because I shall neither find among Men an Allowance of Time to Read, nor of Thought, much less to, Consider what I Write; nor so much as of Those who will Receive what is Written, so far as to Recompence the Charge of Printing: So much do Men <hi>seek</hi> All Things, rather than the Things that pertain to this <hi>Kingdom of Jesus Christ:</hi> But so far as I can, I will give the Strength in short, of what would be much more Apparantly Strong in Large and full.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> 1. The <hi>Lamb</hi> is <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords; King of Kings, &amp;c.</hi> is a Title most Significant of a Great <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> and <hi>Ʋniversal Monarchy:</hi> It is given to <hi>God, 1 Tim.</hi> 6. 15. the onely Supream, Absolute, Independent, Paramount <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,</hi> and that as Introducing Christ into his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> not done at the <hi>Ascension</hi> of Christ, but in his <hi>proper Time;</hi> It is given to <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> in part; <hi>King of Kings,</hi> Dan. Chap. 2. 37. as the <hi>Golden Head</hi> of that <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Ʋniversal Monarchy;</hi> Styled <hi>Dreadful</hi> and <hi>Terrible;</hi> which howevnr Opposite to that <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> and in Delay of it; yet in regard of <hi>Ʋ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversal Monarchy,</hi> had something <hi>Typical</hi> of it, and was a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> to it: He hath also this <hi>Title,</hi> Revel. 19. <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on his Vesture,</hi> and on his <hi>Thigh</hi> particularly, as most Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant of him, who descended from the <hi>Thigh</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and of <hi>David;</hi> In Honour of which <hi>Descent,</hi> was undoubtedly <hi>putting</hi> the <hi>Hand under</hi> the <hi>Thigh,</hi> in use in the <hi>Patriarchal Time</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> in Swearing. Now then both the <hi>Name</hi> the <hi>Lamb,</hi> and the <hi>Title</hi> on the <hi>Vesture</hi> and <hi>Thigh,</hi> are Expressions of the Humane Nature of the <hi>Mediator,</hi> so Innocent, so Spotless, and the <hi>Great Sacrifice;</hi> Therefore before the <hi>Mediatory King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome deliver'd up,</hi> while h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> stands in the place of the <hi>Lamb</hi> in a <hi>Vesture</hi> on his <hi>Thigh,</hi> as the Son of <hi>Abraham Heir of the World,</hi> and on the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>David</hi> his <hi>Father;</hi> that is, as <hi>Mediator,</hi> he must be an <hi>Ʋniversal Monarch,</hi> which he hath not been yet; for he must <hi>overcome the Ten Kings,</hi> that he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appear such; and the <hi>Heavens</hi> must <hi>open to him,</hi> so that that <hi>Kingdom</hi> cannot have yet been; Nor can such strict Notions of the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> be fit to express the <hi>Eternal Kingdom,</hi> when <hi>God</hi> is <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All;</hi> so it must be a <hi>Kingdom</hi> yet to come, and not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106748:9"/> in <hi>Eternity,</hi> that is so described; and must be therefore a <hi>Kingdom</hi> of a peculiar <hi>Oeconomy</hi> between this <hi>present Time</hi> and the <hi>state of Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> 2. The second Scripture I insist upon therefore is, 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 24. Then commeth the End, &amp;c.</hi> Herein are several Things Asserted by the Apostle of undeniable Strength, for such a peculiar <hi>Kingdom,</hi> to which <hi>I</hi> shall have continual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course. At the present <hi>I</hi> urge Two Expressions. 1. The <hi>Son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> shall be <hi>subject. 2. God</hi> shall be <hi>All in All.</hi> Now as the <hi>Learned Adversary</hi> says, What Time can there be, when the <hi>Son,</hi> viz. <hi>as Man,</hi> is not <hi>subject?</hi> That it should be said, <hi>He shall be subject.</hi> Or, when is not <hi>God All in All,</hi> in regard of the <hi>Son,</hi> that it should be said, <hi>He shall be All in All?</hi> Most True! Not when he was Here in his First <hi>Coming;</hi> For then <hi>He hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himself;</hi> Not now in <hi>Heaven,</hi> for He is at the <hi>Right Hand</hi> of <hi>God, Sitting</hi> and <hi>Standing,</hi> which speaks Him <hi>subordinate,</hi> and <hi>God All in All;</hi> Nor in the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity;</hi> For then of all Times the <hi>Son</hi> is <hi>subject</hi> as to his <hi>Mediatory Kingdom,</hi> it having Aceomplish'd all it is to do: So that though the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature</hi> shall be All over <hi>Glorious</hi> with the <hi>Glory</hi> the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Word</hi> had with the <hi>Father before the World began;</hi> and in the <hi>Everlasting Glory</hi> of his Accomplished <hi>Mediatorship,</hi> as having <hi>brought</hi> all his <hi>Saints</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Father;</hi> yet even This is under <hi>God All in All,</hi> and not a distinct <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity,</hi> according to the Apostle's express Doctrine, and in the very Reason of the Thing: There must be therefore some peculiar <hi>Oeconomy,</hi> wherein the <hi>Son</hi> is so <hi>distinctly Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> in the <hi>Humanity;</hi> That it is as if <hi>God</hi> were not <hi>All in All,</hi> but had (as <hi>I</hi> may speak with Reverence) a <hi>Second;</hi> or as <hi>Scripture</hi> speaks, a <hi>Fellow</hi> in his <hi>Glory;</hi> and as if the <hi>Son was not subject,</hi> because his <hi>Kingdom</hi> is now a Distinct <hi>Kingdom,</hi> though United with the <hi>Fathers,</hi> as the <hi>Rain-bow</hi> with the <hi>Sun;</hi> and when this <hi>Oeconomy</hi> ceases, the <hi>Son</hi> returns to be <hi>subject,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> to <hi>be All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas therefore <hi>I</hi> find the <hi>Worthy Opponent,</hi> with other Excellent Men, giving this Account of the <hi>Son's Delivering up of the Kingdom,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of <hi>God</hi> being <hi>All in All;</hi> viz. That the <hi>Kingdom</hi> as it is now Administred by way of Conflict, and gradual Acquist, or Conquest, is upon the <hi>perfect Conquest Deliver'd up,</hi> and so <hi>God</hi> becomes <hi>All in All;</hi> when <hi>Sin, Death, Satan,</hi> and all <hi>Enemies</hi> are <hi>subdued;</hi> Christ hath then no more
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106748:10"/> to do by way of Conquest; But <hi>God</hi> hath a <hi>peaceable Kingdom</hi> free from <hi>Enemies,</hi> and so Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Flows into Fruition and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of Christ as the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>King</hi> in <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> and of his <hi>Saints</hi> United by himself to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Father, All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Truth</hi> of all This <hi>I</hi> do most Heartily and Fully Acknowledge in the Main; But that it satisfies the Apostle's Sense and Assertion, <hi>I</hi> cannot Agree.</p>
            <p>Because <hi>I</hi> think such an Impropriety of Expression ought not without the most Absolute Necessity to be Charged upon the Apostle; <hi>viz.</hi> That when the <hi>Son</hi> is Truly said now to be in Action and Contest against <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Satan,</hi> and the <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> of the <hi>Divine Kingdom</hi> on one side, and effectually work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by his <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Word</hi> in his <hi>Saints</hi> on Earth, and <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ding</hi> for Them in <hi>Heaven</hi> on the other side, in the <hi>highest Subordination</hi> and <hi>Subjection</hi> to the <hi>Father's pleasure,</hi> and the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> but <hi>One; He</hi> should then be said Distinguishingly to <hi>Reign;</hi> and when All is Done, and all Opposition Conquer'd, and no more to Do, but to Enjoy; <hi>He</hi> should then be said <hi>to Deliver up the Kingdom,</hi> and to become <hi>subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This so <hi>Great Impropriety,</hi> and even <hi>Confusion</hi> of <hi>Language</hi> in the <hi>Apostle, I</hi> can by no means Subscribe to.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, There appears no Absolute Necessity of such <hi>Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety;</hi> Because <hi>Scripture</hi> giving so Broad and Remarkable Descriptions of so <hi>peculiar</hi> a <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> to the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> as the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> that is to be between this present State of <hi>Things,</hi> and the State of <hi>Eternity;</hi> which <hi>Kingdom</hi> ceasing at its proper Time, is said to be <hi>Delivered up;</hi> The <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom</hi> will Admirably Agree with the <hi>Apostle</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of the <hi>Son's Reigning,</hi> and of his <hi>Delivery up</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and becoming <hi>subject,</hi> and <hi>God being All in All;</hi> which <hi>He</hi> was pleased in an <hi>Oeconomy▪</hi> not to Appear to be Alone, for the sake of the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> till this <hi>Oeconomy</hi> shall cease. All this Admirably Agrees, but Nothing else can or will Agree; as we shall further shew.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> go on therefore to observe <hi>Scripture</hi> setting out this <hi>pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar</hi> and <hi>distinct Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Son of Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument 3. I</hi> Argue in the next place from that Scripture; <hi>As my Father hath appointed to Me a Kingdom;</hi> so <hi>I Appoint to You a Kingdom, that You may Eat and Drink with Me at my Table in my Kingdom;</hi> and <hi>Sit on Thrones Judging the Tribes of</hi> Israel: Luke 22. 29, 30.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106748:10"/>
            <p>Here are Three Things, which do assure us, the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> is a <hi>Kingdom</hi> distinct to the <hi>Humane Nature of Christ,</hi> and disserent from the <hi>Sitting of Christ at the Right Hand of God</hi> in his <hi>Humane Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That it is a <hi>Kingdom</hi> distinct to the <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Kingdom of the Eternal Word</hi> as in Himself, nor as the <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> is considered as United to the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> is Evident; in that it is not a Natural Essential <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but a <hi>Constitutive Appointed Kingdom,</hi> Appointed by the Gracious Pleasure and Arbitrement of the <hi>Father,</hi> and of the same Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitive Nature with the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Saints:</hi> For saith <hi>Christ, As the Father hath Appointed Me,</hi> so <hi>I Appoint You a Kingdom;</hi> But the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> and of the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> as United to the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> and Communicating with it, is an <hi>Essential,</hi> and not a <hi>Constitutive Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Kingdom</hi> Christ speaks of, cannot on this Account also be the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> Christ hath now at the <hi>Right Hand of God:</hi> For his <hi>Saints</hi> do not yet sit on <hi>Thrones</hi> with <hi>Him, Judging the Twelve Tribes of</hi> Israel, as he promised in his <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Christ calls it <hi>his Kingdom,</hi> as distinct from his <hi>Fathers,</hi> and uses those Familiar Expressions of <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking</hi> in his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> which together with that of <hi>Judging the Twelve Tribes</hi> Assure, it is not the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity,</hi> when <hi>God shall be All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument 4. I</hi> Argue from <hi>Revel.</hi> 3. 21. Christ distinguishes his <hi>Throne</hi> from his <hi>Fathers Throne;</hi> not only, by saying, <hi>My Thoone,</hi> and <hi>my Fathers Throne;</hi> but by a Distinction more Real, <hi>He overcame,</hi> and is <hi>Set down with his Father on his Throne.</hi> From whence it is Evident, the <hi>Thrones</hi> are two distinct <hi>Thrones;</hi> Christ was on his <hi>Fathers,</hi> He was not on his Own.</p>
            <p>How Evident then is it, Christ had a <hi>Throne</hi> in his Eye, that was not his <hi>Fathers,</hi> but his <hi>Own,</hi> on which he knew he should Sit hereafter, but was not yet set down; And it was such a <hi>Throne</hi> as his <hi>Saints</hi> might sit down upon with him; but on <hi>his Fathers Throne,</hi> They could not <hi>sit down;</hi> He alone can sit on that, <hi>All</hi> being <hi>subject</hi> to him: So the <hi>Throne</hi> of Christ cannot be a <hi>Throne</hi> he hath yet; nor can it be the <hi>Throne of Eternity,</hi> because then the Son is <hi>subject,</hi> and hath not a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct <hi>Throne,</hi> but as United to the Father, and by him All
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106748:11"/> his <hi>Saints</hi> are with him so United, and so <hi>God</hi> is <hi>All in All,</hi> and Christ in the <hi>Glory</hi> he had with the <hi>Father</hi> before the <hi>World began; viz.</hi> As United with the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> in regard of the <hi>Humane Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum. 5. To sit at my Right Hand, and at my Left, in My Kingdom,</hi> saith our Lord, <hi>is not Mine to Giue; But it shall be Given to Them, for whom it is prepared of My Father. Mat.</hi> 20. 20. It is Evident, this is not the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the Eternal Word; For neither is there any <hi>sitting</hi> on his <hi>Right Hand</hi> or <hi>Left,</hi> on that <hi>Throne</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Word;</hi> nor would he, as the <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal VVord,</hi> Say, <hi>It is not Mine to give;</hi> Nor can it be the Kingly State, wherein Christ in his <hi>Humane Nature</hi> now <hi>Sits on the Right Hand of God;</hi> For There can be no <hi>Sitting on his Right, or on his Left Hand,</hi> as he <hi>Sits</hi> now; whoever should sit now on the <hi>Left Hand of Christ,</hi> must sit between Him, and the <hi>Father,</hi> on whos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Right Hand</hi> He sits Immediately, and none near Him: It must be therefore in the Kingdom the <hi>Father</hi> Appoints to Him, and is most distinct to Him; As in Humane Courts, the King's eldest Son hath a distinct▪ Court Appointed to Him, deriving yet All its Glory from the Kings Court, and wherein the King Appoints Supremely notwithstanding; So the <hi>Throne of God,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> is in that distinct <hi>Kingdom;</hi> Yet it is so Oeconomiz'd as to be distinct; and <hi>All Things are put under the Lamb,</hi> as so distinct in that his Kingdom, except he Alone who <hi>put All Things under Him,</hi> and who dwells in it, as in his <hi>Tahernacle,</hi> to Fill it with his Glory, and yet Gives it Leave to be distinct.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 6. I Argue from Innumerable Scriptures put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wherein Christ speaks of his Kingdom as to come, and not yet come; So that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en it is so come, It may very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be said to Begin, as <hi>Mat:</hi> 19. 27. Christ tells <hi>Peter,</hi> and the other Disciples, <hi>You that have Followed me, shall in the Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,</hi> when the <hi>Son of Man sits on the Throne of his Glory, sit on Twelve Thrones, &amp;c.</hi> Shewing plainly the Time of <hi>Sitting on the Throne of his Glory,</hi> was not to be till hereafter▪ Joyn this with <hi>Mat. 25. 31. When the Son of Man shall come in his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and <hi>All his Holy Angels with Him, then shall he sit on the Throne of his Glory,</hi> And <hi>All shall be gather'd together before Him, &amp;c.</hi> Here we have the <hi>Coming of Christ</hi> in his Glory, Joyn'd with this <hi>Sitting on the Throne of his Glory;</hi> and that design'd to be, not before <hi>All gather'd before Him</hi> at the Judgment, and when
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106748:11"/> his <hi>Saints shall be in Glory;</hi> Again, 2 Tim. 4. 1. <hi>I charge thee before God, and our Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> who shall <hi>Judge the Quick and the Dead at his Kingdom,</hi> His <hi>Appearing,</hi> and His <hi>Judging</hi> the <hi>the Quick and the Dead,</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom</hi> are Joyn'd together: In the Parable of the <hi>Talents, Luke</hi> 19. 11. One Principal End, and Scope of it was to tell Them, who thought the <hi>Kingdom of God should Immediately Appear;</hi> that It should not <hi>Immediately Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear;</hi> But that he was to go into a <hi>Far Countrey</hi> to <hi>Receive a Kingdom,</hi> and to <hi>Return, viz.</hi> in <hi>his Kingdom:</hi> Now the end of a <hi>Parable</hi> is Argumentative, and Christ spake the <hi>Parable,</hi> as one Great End for this very purpose, to Teach this, and to Arrest the Thoughts of the <hi>Immediate Appearance of the Kingdom of Christ;</hi> For it is said, He Added that <hi>Parable,</hi> because he was Nigh to <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> whither he was <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to Receive</hi> a Fore▪ Representation of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in the <hi>spreading of Garments,</hi> the <hi>strowing of Palms,</hi> and <hi>Riding on the Foal of an Ass,</hi> as the King Fore-told by <hi>Zechary,</hi> and to Receive the <hi>Hosannahs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the people.</hi> All which Ceremonies shew his Kingdom to be the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Son of Man.</hi> And it was, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Christ had been then immediately to Open <hi>his Kingdom:</hi> But he plainly Declares there would be Opportunity for his Servants to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove Receiv'd <hi>Talents</hi> for a long Time first, and then to have their Reward Adjusted to Them in <hi>Ten</hi> or <hi>Five Cities;</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing also the Nature of <hi>his Kingdom</hi> to be <hi>Oeconomical</hi> under that other <hi>Emblem,</hi> and not the State of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> when <hi>God</hi> shall be <hi>All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, <hi>Matth</hi> 16. 26, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7. Christ having said, <hi>The Son of Man shall come in the Glory of his Father, &amp;c.</hi> Immediately Adds, There are <hi>some standing h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re who shall not Taste of Death, till they see the Son of Man coming in his Kingdom.</hi> Or as in <hi>Mark, Till the Kingdom of God cometh with Power.</hi> This he said, while his Thoughts were Vehement, Warm, and even Hot upon the <hi>Coming to Reward everyone according to his Works.</hi> He speaks with a <hi>Pathos,</hi> a great Earnestness <hi>Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly I say unto you, &amp;c.</hi> So that thereby he shews, his Kingdom shall be to <hi>Reward every one according to his Works</hi> The only Doubt is How Christ could say, <hi>There be some standing here, who shall not Taste D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath,</hi> till then: The Answer is That Great Pre-Representation of his <hi>Kingdm,</hi> (which <hi>Peter, 2 Epist.</hi> 1. 16. in words so near Christ▪s, calls his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Coming;</hi> when, saith he, We were Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witnesse of his Majesty.) <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Transfiguration</hi> followed the Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106748:12"/> of Christ, [There be <hi>Some, &amp;c.</hi>] in every of the Three <hi>Evangelists,</hi> who Record the <hi>Transfiguration;</hi> which shews the <hi>Transfiguration</hi> is a great Type of that distinct <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> supplied with the Beams of Glory, from the <hi>Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty,</hi> as with that Voice, <hi>This is my beloved Son, &amp;c.</hi> And yet at a distance from the <hi>Glory of Christ,</hi> that it might not be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shin'd; but <hi>Christ</hi> as a <hi>Man be</hi> in <hi>visible Glory,</hi> and his <hi>Saints</hi> with Him; Both Those of the <hi>First Resurrection,</hi> as <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias,</hi> and Those of the <hi>Living remaining Saints,</hi> as <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> who had yet but an Inferiour Share in that <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were yet the <hi>peculiar chosen Witnesses</hi> of that <hi>Appearance in Glory,</hi> and the <hi>Some</hi> pointed at by Christ, who should see it; and of that same <hi>Sort</hi> and <hi>Generation,</hi> (as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Imports) that they were of, There should be, <hi>viz. Saints,</hi> who shall not <hi>Die,</hi> or <hi>Taste of Death,</hi> but be <hi>changed,</hi> and so shall <hi>See the Son of Man come in his Kingdom, and the Kingdom of God come with Power;</hi> and be <hi>Witnesses</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Now let All These Scripturrs be laid together, and it will Appear, So <hi>Judicious</hi> an <hi>Adversary</hi> will have no Reason of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, that it is said, There is a <hi>Kingdom of Christ to Begin,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his Kingdom be Truly said to have been also <hi>from the Beginning;</hi> Nor that it shall <hi>End,</hi> seeing All the manner of speaking concerning it, shews it to be the <hi>Oecenomy</hi> of a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> so proper to the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> that the <hi>Kingdom of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther All in All</hi> cannot consist with; as shall be further shewn in the next <hi>Argument,</hi> and therefore that it must End, when the <hi>Kingdom is Deliver'd up,</hi> as to the <hi>Oeconomy;</hi> and yet in all Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentials of the Glory of Christ, and of his <hi>Saints▪</hi> it continues for ever, as was Foretold of It.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 6. The yet Fullest and most Conclusive Argument of so Distinct a <hi>Kingdom</hi> that hath not yet been, and that must <hi>End</hi> and be <hi>Given up,</hi> when the State of <hi>Eternity</hi> enters, is, That the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> hath most certainly Fix▪d the Bounds, when this Distinct Kingdom can, and before which it cannot Begin; how long the State of it can Last, and when it must End, and be <hi>Given up,</hi> and that by one single Note of the <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing Enemies;</hi> and herein it is as Positive and Assertive as it is in any <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> for both the Beginning and the End.</p>
            <p>Let us then observe Two Remarks to be Found in <hi>Scripture,</hi> concerning the <hi>Enemies of Christ</hi> being <hi>put under him;</hi> One is,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106748:12"/> The making the <hi>Enemies</hi> of Christ the <hi>Footstool of his Feet</hi> *.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The Other is, The putting the <hi>Enemies of Christ</hi> Low under his Feet, expressed by the <hi>peculiar</hi> Force of the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>viz</hi> To bring to the State of no Motion or Action. The First <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>making the Enemies of Christ</hi> the <hi>Footstool of his Feet,</hi> we shall find peculiarly Fix'd as the <hi>Epoch,</hi> or <hi>Beginning</hi> of this distinct <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> And it must continue until the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, The <hi>putting Them quite under his Feet,</hi> by that perfect di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguishing <hi>Catargesis,</hi> or Evacuation of All Power, Motion or Action, which is to be Fixt at the Period or End of <hi>Christ's Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us then look back on all those <hi>Scriptures</hi> that Joyn the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Coming of Christ</hi> together so evidently, that there must be an <hi>Illustrious Kingdom of Christ at his coming.</hi> Now then the Time and Moment of his <hi>Coming</hi> is Determined by this very Note of his <hi>Enemies made the Footstool of his Feet;</hi> For so <hi>the Lord Jehovah</hi> said to our <hi>Adonai, our Lord the King,</hi> Psal. 110. 1▪ <hi>Sit Thou at my Right Hand, till I make Thy Eemies the Footstool of thy Feet.</hi> That is, <hi>I</hi> intend Thee a Great, a Distinct <hi>Kingdom;</hi> the Date of its Beginning shall be, not Immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at thy <hi>Resurrection</hi> or <hi>Ascension,</hi> but at the Time <hi>I</hi> have De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to make <hi>Thy Enemies Thy Footstool;</hi> Till then, <hi>Thou shalt Sit at my Right Hand.</hi> Observe then, when <hi>Christ Reigns,</hi> He <hi>Comes;</hi> while He <hi>Sits,</hi> He does not <hi>Come:</hi> He <hi>Sits</hi> and does not <hi>Come;</hi> and so does not <hi>Reign as a King,</hi> as that Great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> till the Time the <hi>Divine Power</hi> Constitutes Him in Power, as by a Solemn Commission, to make his <hi>Enemies Crouch down as the Footstool of his Feet▪</hi> He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sits, as the <hi>Apostle</hi> speaks, <hi>Expecting, He Sits at the Right Hand of God;</hi> yet not at his <hi>Akme,</hi> not at his Highest Point▪ as <hi>Son of Man</hi> and <hi>Mediator;</hi> He Sits Expecting in Patience, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, The <hi>Patience of the Kingdom of Christ;</hi> till his <hi>Enemies</hi> are so Constituted his <hi>Footstool,</hi> for then He knows <hi>He shall Reign.</hi> In the mean time, though every Thing <hi>shall be put under Him,</hi> ere the <hi>End;</hi> yet we see Them <hi>not put under Him,</hi> saith the <hi>Apostle,</hi> though He be <hi>Ascended, Heb.</hi> 2▪ 5. 10. And because it may be Thought Christ is indeed in the <hi>Heavens,</hi> where All Things are in a State of <hi>Subjection to him.</hi> But we cannot see it by the Eye of Sense, howbeit we may see it by the Eye of Faith; No, saith the <hi>Apostle, The subjection of the World to come,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106748:13"/> whereof we speak;</hi> and <hi>the putting All Things under him,</hi> as the <hi>Second Adam, Lord of All;</hi> according to <hi>Psalm</hi> 8. Cannot be seen, as come to pass so much as by Faith; though as to <hi>Come,</hi> it may be so seen; For we see Him by Faith, <hi>Crown'd with Glory and Honour,</hi> which cannot be seen by Sense: But we do not yet see <hi>All Things put under him,</hi> so much as by Faith. All which put together, Admirably clears the First Part, that this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct <hi>Kingdom</hi> begins with the <hi>Enemies of Christ made his Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stool.</hi> Christ therefore waits till the <hi>Father,</hi> till <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Jehovah</hi> give him <hi>Commission,</hi> and Delegate Power to Him, to bring down <hi>his Enemies;</hi> so as that They may be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced first as the <hi>Footstool of his Feet,</hi> that what hath been long given him by Decree, may be brought Actually to pass in his <hi>Kingdom</hi> beginning.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Tee Other or Second Remark upon the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> by his <hi>Enemies brought under him,</hi> is this, They must be <hi>brought quite under his Feet,</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may signifie; but is especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>utter Disannulling,</hi> so often mentioned; for when it is come to that, then the <hi>Kingdom</hi> in this <hi>Oeconomy</hi> is to End, and to be <hi>Delivered up;</hi> and therefore this very Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression is Applied to each <hi>Enemy,;</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is Applied to All <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary Authority</hi> and <hi>Power;</hi> He shall <hi>put it down,</hi> particularly the <hi>Monarchick Power</hi> of <hi>Nebuchadnezar's Image;</hi> All shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Delivering up of the Kingdom</hi> be so <hi>brought to nought,</hi> as to be in no possibility of further Motion or Action, as shall be shewn; this is declar'd, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 24. It is Applied yet most particularly to the <hi>Beast,</hi> to the <hi>Antichristian Power,</hi> that is Exemplarily and before the Rest so Annull'd, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2. 8. It is Applied to the <hi>Devil,</hi> having the <hi>Power of Death, Heb.</hi> 2. 14. It is lastly Applied to <hi>Death it self, 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 27. To every one of these, who ever pleases to search shall find. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Catargesis</hi> Applied; and this very last <hi>Catargesis,</hi> or <hi>Destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Death,</hi> is plac'd the utmost Pillar of this Kingdom in <hi>Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy;</hi> for then it is immediately <hi>Delivered up to God All in All,</hi> and the <hi>Son subject,</hi> as the <hi>Apostle</hi> most Peremptorily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines, <hi>v.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6.</p>
            <p>There remains therefore the Consideration of the <hi>middle Space</hi> between the Beginning and the End of the <hi>Oecanomy.</hi> Now this <hi>Scripture</hi> hath, as to any Doctrinal part, that hath come to my Thoughts, left to the plain and undoubted Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the Thing; That at the Beginning of the Kingdom,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106748:13"/> and when Christ comes in it, All must be put under him, so as to be the <hi>Footstool of his Feet;</hi> And then All must be disan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null'd, Ras'd out of all possibility of Contrary Action, or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the End, and not till the End; They must needs be as the <hi>Footstool of his Feet,</hi> They must serve his State, and his Triumph all the Time of his <hi>Reign:</hi> And a <hi>Reign</hi> must be a space of Time, The very word <hi>Reign</hi> Implys a space, and as it is a Kingdom at the End of the <hi>Four Monarchies,</hi> it must be so, else It cannot Answer to them; and seeing he cannot begin to Reign, till his Enemies are his <hi>Footstool,</hi> nor can he cease to Reign, till They are so Evacuated; The State can neither go Backward nor Forward; Not Backward, because the Motion that is to be made, is Forward to Final disannul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; Not Forward till the End, for the Apostle hath Fix'd that Time for the Bringing all Enemy Power to Absolute no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; whatever space of Reign therefore there is, The State must be the same, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Enemies of Christ</hi> must be the <hi>Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stool of his Feet</hi> serving so, as Captive Princes, the Glory of the Triumph, and Victory of Christ, not utterly Remov'd, till the very last, that the Victory may not be Forgotten.</p>
            <p>But though the Doctrinal Parts of Scripture have not Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us the space of this Kingdom but darkly, and <hi>Enigmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally;</hi> Yet <hi>Prophetical Scripture</hi> compar'd with Doctrinal, hath Fully declar'd it to be the space of the 1000 <hi>Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> hath given a very notable, though My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterious<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Pet.</hi> 3▪ 7, 8, 9.</note> Intimation of it, by Applying on one side close to the mention of the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> that Great Remark that one Day with the Lord is as a 1000 <hi>Years,</hi> and with that Solemn Preface, usual in such Great Mysteries in <hi>Scripture;</hi> Let not this <hi>One Thing lye Hid from you,</hi> not meaning sure that Great Natural Principle of the <hi>Eternity of God,</hi> All are presum'd to Know, to which All Past, Present, and to Come is a Just now; But that the <hi>One Day of Judgment,</hi> the same with the <hi>Day of Christ's coming in his Kingdom,</hi> as we have seen, is with the Lord as a 1000 <hi>Yetrs,</hi> and on the other side a 1000. <hi>Years, viz.</hi> of past Time, is but as <hi>One day;</hi> From whence He Inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially Goes on upon the Supposition, God hath design'd each 1000 <hi>Years</hi> past, to be as but <hi>One day</hi> of the Worlds Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from its <hi>Creation</hi> to its Renovation; Of this he presently Treats upon that Supposition; saith He, the <hi>Lord is not slack, &amp;c.</hi> But though this might be more Advantagiously discours'd then
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106748:14"/> is generally Apprehended, I have not Room for it now.</p>
            <p>Nor can I stay yet on the mention of the 1000 <hi>Years, Rev.</hi> 20. as It shall be Abundantly shown; That They cannot possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be understood of any past Time, but what I shall Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, shall be by a Compare of Them with Doctrinal Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to show, that They so Begin, They so Consist, They so End, as to demonstrate to any Wise Serious Considerer, They so Exactly Agree with the Beginning, with the middle space, with the End of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> in the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> hitherto discours'd in that Note of Enemies, as that They must be the very Space of that <hi>Kingdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. These 1000 Years Begin with the Laying the <hi>Enemies of Christ,</hi> from the very Beginning, of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> at <hi>his Feet;</hi> as the <hi>Footstool of his Feet, viz.</hi> All the <hi>Idolatrous Kings,</hi> and their Greats and their Smalls, as slain, that is, Condemn'd <hi>with the Sword of Christ's Mouth,</hi> lying as the Dead, Captiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and Exil'd for the 1000 <hi>Years</hi> in the <hi>Four Corners of the Earth,</hi> and so the Trophies of the Victory, and <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> For These Slain, or, as They are call'd also Dead, are only, as we speak, <hi>Dead in Law,</hi> or <hi>Condemn'd,</hi> Rais'd from their Sleep in the Dust, into a State of <hi>Contempt and Dishonour,</hi> to a State of Living Death, or Dying Life, who with Horror Behold the <hi>Glory of Christ,</hi> and of his Saints, and are the Spectacles, and Monuments of his Power, and Conquest before Angels, Saints, and one Another; and not Able, being so Fetter'd with the Rays of that Kingdom, <note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 149. 8.</note> as Persons in Strongest Gives of Iron, to stir or make the least Attempt against it, and as Captives not Slain, (as <hi>David</hi> said, <hi>Slay them not, least my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple forget,</hi> &amp;c.) but so Fetter'd, They are not <hi>Cast into the Lake,</hi> that They may be such Appearing Monuments, and Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. 2. <hi>Sathan,</hi> with all the Hosts of Fallen Angels, is in same manner <hi>Bound, Chain'd,</hi> and <hi>Seal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d▪</hi> up in the <hi>Abyss</hi> through the Potency of the <hi>Divine Kingdom,</hi> He cannot, as now Tempt and Deceive; Yet He is not <hi>Cast into the Lake</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but is Forc'd as it were to a Quiet, though undoubtedly with Highest Rage and Horror; But it is now especially, that the <hi>Crutified Jesus</hi> Appearing in Glory, is seen to spoil Principalities and Powers, and <hi>to make a show of them openly</hi> for the 1000 <hi>Years,</hi> not denying it vertually done on his <hi>Cross.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Antichristian</hi> State only is uader the <hi>Catargesis,</hi> or utter Final even Annihilation as to All Action; For it being the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106748:14"/> Counterfeit of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> All its State, as it is most Exemplary in Punishment, so it is for ever destroy'd by this Glorious Appearance; or as the Apostle calls it, the <hi>Epiphaneia</hi> of Christ, and the so long Continuance of the True Kingdom of the Great <hi>High Priest,</hi> the <hi>Melchisedec,</hi> the Supreme <hi>Prophet;</hi> So the <hi>Beast</hi> and the <hi>False Prophet,</hi> and <hi>Antichristian Church,</hi> are all <hi>Cast into the Lake of an Eternal Burning,</hi> never to Rise any more; <hi>Rev: 14. 9. c. 19. 17. &amp;c.</hi> All such pretences to Christ being for ever cut off, and whatever is now to be done, is to be done by Bare-fac'd, Hellish Malice, as in <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus Jesut Christ, who had from his very <hi>Resurrection gone out,</hi> (as the Opposite Discourse says) <hi>Conquering,</hi> and to <hi>Conquer</hi> does in the End thus <hi>Conquer; Rev</hi> 6. 2 For it is ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> observable, he went out <hi>Conquering,</hi> so that there would still be a Reserve, that <hi>He still might Conquer:</hi> For though he <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd Paganism,</hi> yet still the <hi>Dragon</hi> Gave his <hi>Seat, Power,</hi> and Great <hi>Authority</hi> to the <hi>Beast;</hi> Christ sets his <hi>Right Foot on the Sea,</hi> and <hi>Left Foot on the Earth,</hi> in so much of <hi>Conquest,</hi> as Appear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in the <hi>Reformation;</hi> But yet, till the <hi>Battel of Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geddon,</hi> till the <hi>Sword goes out of his Mouth;</hi> at the <hi>Feast of the Fowls,</hi> which will not be, however My Learned Adversary Interpret it, till Christ Appear <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> and till his Enemies are made his <hi>Footstool,</hi> his <hi>Conquest</hi> will not be so, but that he may still <hi>Conquer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then All Enemies shall lye still in a Captive State, even as <hi>Sathan</hi> Bound; So <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> stir not during the 1000 <hi>Years:</hi> But then the Rays of Glory withdrawing, not so as that the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> should End, but that it should give occasion to its highest Act of disannulling All Enemies, by such a short Suspension of its Beams, as here below; which <hi>Sathan</hi> and those <hi>Captiv'd Dead,</hi> not <hi>Thrown into the Lake,</hi> finding They make that their Brisk, but last Attempt; Out of which, the Assailed Saints are <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ught up</hi> by Christ, and out of a short <hi>Laodicean</hi> Abatement of Former Fervors; Christ <hi>spewing out</hi> any Further Church-State, even on the <hi>New Earth;</hi> So they are <hi>Caught up,</hi> I say, even They which <hi>Overcome,</hi> which are every one, not One of them Lost, to <hi>Sit down with Christ on his Throne;</hi> And then <hi>Fire,</hi> not as in a <hi>Second Conflagration,</hi> as is suppos'd against me, but in place of the Beams of the Glory of Christ in his Kingdom, that did before <hi>Fetter Sathan,</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106748:15"/> the Condemn'd, called the <hi>Dead,</hi> or Mystically and Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> Now they become Lightnings of pure and perfect Fury and Justice prepared to Final Execution and Judgment, and Sweeping Them down into the <hi>Lake,</hi> even the <hi>Dead,</hi> whose <hi>Number is as the Sand of the Sea,</hi> Exil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in the <hi>Four Corners</hi> of the <hi>Earth;</hi> So <hi>Satan</hi> is first Cast into the <hi>Lake,</hi> as long ago Condemn'd; And the <hi>Dead</hi> are, as by an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal and Particular Judgment, and as by a Recollection and Recapitulation of the former <hi>Judgment,</hi> at the Beginning of the Thousand Years, and of all the <hi>Dead,</hi> from the several Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles of <hi>Death,</hi> from whence They came▪ then Judg'd, who are not <hi>Found in the Book of Life;</hi> by a most particular setting All their <hi>Works in order before them;</hi> and especially that Testimony against them, That They were not <hi>found written in the Book of Life,</hi> even of the <hi>first Resurrection</hi> of the Thousand Years: For on such the <hi>second Death can have no power;</hi> Then the <hi>Dead</hi> and all further <hi>power of Death</hi> and <hi>Destruction</hi> are shut up together with <hi>Satan,</hi> the <hi>Prince of the Power of Death</hi> in one <hi>Lake, Burning with Fire and Brimstone;</hi> And so as much as Divinest <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Types</hi> can do, the <hi>Eternal Punishment</hi> of the <hi>wicked Angels</hi> and <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi> even for <hi>ever</hi> and <hi>ever</hi> is Assur'd. For however <hi>I</hi> may be misdeem'd, <hi>I</hi> have not, I dare not Intimate the least Thought, as if the <hi>Punishment</hi> of the <hi>Wicked</hi> were not <hi>Eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>I</hi> have given the most Agreeable <hi>Paraphrase,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my whole <hi>Prophetick Scheme, I</hi> submit it to every Considering Person's Acceptance; But I Appeal with all possible Confidence to Heaven and Earth, whether this <hi>Book of the Revelation</hi> in this last part of it, be not in a <hi>Prophetical</hi> Representation, as Admirably and Perfectly Compos'd, to set out in matter of Fact the <hi>Apostolical Doctrine</hi> in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Particulars, as can be given or expected, of the <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mier of Christ</hi> first made the <hi>Footstool of Christ,</hi> at the <hi>Thousand Years</hi> Beginning.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of that Great <hi>Catargesis,</hi> or Bringing all that Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary Power to a perfect Nullity at the end of the <hi>Thousand Years;</hi> even as at the Beginning of the <hi>Thousand Years</hi> The <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristian City, Church, Beast,</hi> and <hi>false Prophets,</hi> were Destroyed out of all Appearance of Action and Motion, as hath been Declared.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of the Posture, <hi>Enemies of Christ</hi> lying at the Feet of Christ, being the <hi>Footstool</hi> of Them, and not being able to stir, or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106748:15"/> Disturb the Peace of <hi>his Kingdom,</hi> during the <hi>Thousand Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as to the first part, <hi>viz.</hi> Laying the Enemies of Christ at <hi>his Feet,</hi> Christ first proceeds by the <hi>Voice of the Everlasting Gospel,</hi> to Invite to Repentance; then by the <hi>Seven Vials,</hi> Beating down the Impenitent of all Ages, when it had been first said, <hi>He that is filthy, let him be filthy still;</hi> and <hi>He that is Righteous, let him be Righteous still;</hi> shewing that there is no Change when once the Vials begin to play; (for thereunto these Words have especial Reference,) so we hear of nothing but Impenitency all along the <hi>Vials,</hi> even from the <hi>Preaching the everlasting Gospel,</hi> and its full Effect, to the end; compare <hi>Revel.</hi> 14. 6. Chap. 16. 9. 11. Chap. 21. 9. Chap. 22. 11.</p>
            <p>And as thus, There shall be a Time before the Thousand Years <hi>Kingdom</hi> in <hi>Glory,</hi> even 75 years from its Succession to its Glory (by <hi>Daniel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi>) (Chap. 12. 11. Accounts) of Preparation by the <hi>Voices,</hi> Revel. 14. and by the <hi>Vials,</hi> Revel. 16. So there shall be a Time after the Glory of the Thousand Years, wherein there is a <hi>Casting</hi> All into the <hi>Lake,</hi> which is exprest in <hi>Paul's Epistles,</hi> as in Exactest Agreement one with another, by the so often mentioned <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in Preparation to the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering up of the Kingdom to God</hi> and the <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so I have dispatch'd what <hi>I</hi> have Room for in this short Answer, concerning this Point; whereln if any Assertions seem bold, <hi>I</hi> desire, the Scriptures, to which <hi>I</hi> Refer in every Tittle, may be weigh'd one with another; and <hi>I</hi> hope they will not Appear so Bold, but Close <hi>searching</hi> of <hi>Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> come therefore to the Second Point proposed, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> however it Includes, and that very Eminently, the <hi>Fall of Pagan Imperial Rome;</hi> yet it is chiefly prepar'd to the <hi>Destruction</hi> of <hi>Antichristian Rome,</hi> in its yet Continuing State, and to set out the Glory that shall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in the <hi>Kingdom of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Discussing of this will add Light to the former Point; For when it shall, as <hi>I</hi> hope it may Appear, that the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> or as we Translate, <hi>Revelation,</hi> runs with a clear Current, and not only so, but with a strong Torrent unto this Great Distinct <hi>Kingdom</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> as the <hi>Son of Man</hi> (or as that styles him) the <hi>Lamb;</hi> how will it add Belief to the Truth of that <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> seeing all <hi>Prophecies</hi> Center in this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> even the <hi>Mystery of God, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliz'd</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:106748:16"/> by all his Servants the <hi>Prophets</hi> here Centers. Now herein <hi>I</hi> shall not be able in such Straitness of Room, to say the Tenth part of what is to be said; And what <hi>I</hi> do say, (though <hi>I</hi> will do what ever <hi>I</hi> can to Shade my much esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Adversary</hi>) yet the very Nature of the Thing that is to be spoken of, will require some Earnestness: The contrary <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent I</hi> am to oppose, so far as <hi>I</hi> can understand it, is; That the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> spends it self; except some share of Interest, that the <hi>Jews</hi> of those Times may have in it, in the change of <hi>Pagan Imperial Rome,</hi> from <hi>Pagan</hi> to <hi>Christian;</hi> and that this emploies the <hi>Seals,</hi> the <hi>Trumpets;</hi> the <hi>Vials;</hi> And that the <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Years</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi> Bound, are but the Description of the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py State of the <hi>Church</hi> from <hi>Constantine</hi> to the <hi>Turkish Greatness</hi> of Power; and the <hi>New Jerusalem State</hi> of no other Importance but to speak the <hi>Christian Church</hi> in so happy a Change, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Martyrs</hi> are Bless'd with <hi>Christ</hi> in their Spirits, and are in great Honour also here below; Except, as it may be also a <hi>Type,</hi> or an <hi>Emblem</hi> of the Glorious State of the <hi>Kingdom of God and of Christ in Eternity,</hi> in the <hi>New Heaven and Earth,</hi> sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to continue to <hi>Eternity:</hi> All except this is suppos'd to describe the State here below.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Papal and Antihristian Rome,</hi> though it be not excus'd hereby from other Charges, yet the Weight, the main Stroke, the <hi>Hail, each Stone</hi> as a <hi>Talent</hi> that falls in this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> falls quite short of <hi>Papall Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now whithout any Aggravations of the portentousness of such a <hi>Sentiment, I</hi> shall use no other Remonstrance against it, but what will fall in with the Proof <hi>I</hi> shall give, that this <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Book,</hi> wherein all the Wisdom, Ingeny, and Learuing of all Ages and Nations is Assembled, is assign'd to a much more Excellent Purpose; <hi>I</hi> shall give then in brief these Four, Arguments, which shall be all <hi>I</hi> will at this time make use of; but <hi>I</hi> have prepar'd by me a <hi>New Apocalyptical Key,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginuing at the End, moves Baekward to the Beginning of this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and shews, the <hi>Lamb</hi> hath from his <hi>Resurrection</hi> been Guiding and Conducting all Time, and the Events of it, according to the <hi>Types of the Prophecy</hi> given to that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> wherein he is to to be seen in the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Humane Nature;</hi> which as he Received from the <hi>Father,</hi> He will Return and Surrender up to the <hi>Father</hi> at the Time design'd in such a State, that the <hi>Kingdom of God All in All,</hi> may be without any▪
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106748:16"/> shade of an <hi>Enemy,</hi> and Himself and his Saints Inseparably United to the <hi>Father,</hi> and be as <hi>God was, and is from Eternity,</hi> in <hi>perfect Glory</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> to <hi>Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it will be Found, that One very Conspicuous and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent part of this <hi>Prophecy</hi> is indeed taken up, in bringing the <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> to become <hi>Christian</hi> in Name and Proseffion, though it soon after <hi>Apostatized.</hi> This is allowed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> 1. Seeing it hath pleased the Wisdom, the Grace, and Infintie Prescience of our God, to give a <hi>Prophecy</hi> peculiar to the <hi>New Testament,</hi> it cannot with Reverence and Honour to <hi>Him,</hi> be suppos'd, that a <hi>Prophecy</hi> so Admirable in its Frame and Contexture, so Rich, if <hi>I</hi> may be bold so to speak, in its▪ Devices, Emblems, and Figures, and so large in its Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, that It should not Comprehend the State of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Church</hi> to the very last, and to the winding up of Things; especially when it bears so great an Appearadce thae it does so; in not only Joyning, but Wreathing Events into the last End of Things.</p>
            <p>For who can but say, that the Three last Chapters of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> carry a Wonderful Appearance of the Last End of All; and as we shall find the several Parts and Events of the <hi>Prophecy,</hi> do so Lock One into another, that if the End of All be at the Last, there must be some Events coming to pass one after anohter, from the Beginning to the End, without any▪ Gap between; Because the Beginning, the End, and the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Parts of the Prophecy are so enchain'd and enchas'd to and into One Another, as not to be possibly separated from One Another.</p>
            <p>Seeing then, that no One, that Reads the End of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> can but think, it Describes the last End of All, it cannot indeed be otherwise, that so much plain Language can be otherwise understood. If that be so, then, <hi>I</hi> say, the Events of the <hi>Prophecy</hi> are so lincked, there must be a Line of them running strait-forward from the very Beginning to the End; and therefore the <hi>Prophecy</hi> cannot End at <hi>Constantine,</hi> nor leap over Events between, from <hi>Constantine</hi> to the <hi>Turks,</hi> about the Year 1300, and so to the very last End of Things, to the Heavenly State of the Saints in the <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> nor to the Destruction of <hi>Satan</hi> and the <hi>Wicked</hi> in the <hi>Lake,</hi> without the middle Events between. There must be therefore <hi>Antichristian Rome</hi> between <hi>Pagan
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106748:17"/> Rome</hi> and the End, or some other great Event, as that, to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Course of Time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> And if it should be said, <hi>Prophecy</hi> does in its Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent way of speaking, make use of the highest Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, on occasion of any very Remarkable Providence of Mercy or Judgment, taken either from the Glory and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of <hi>Heaven,</hi> or from the <hi>Horrour</hi> and <hi>Wrath</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> as many Instances may seem to bear out, both in the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Testament,</hi> and yet intend only some much less Things of this present World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ. I</hi> Answer, Because there was Scripture still behind to sustain and make good All at last; even these last Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the <hi>Revelation;</hi> the <hi>Objection</hi> may be Allowed in the Main; And what-ever hath been said before in any part of Scripture, or even in the <hi>Revelation</hi> it self, (as Chap. 6. <hi>ult.</hi>) that had not its Fulfilling in its Intention by the Divine Spirit, look'd to this last Issue, it look'd hither; For here it hath its just Fulness of Event, <hi>Measure shaken together, press'd down,</hi> and <hi>running over. I</hi> am perswaded that even <hi>John</hi> 21. 25. Looks no higher: No World but the World <hi>to come,</hi> could <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain All Christ Did</hi> and <hi>Said.</hi> But if this last of <hi>Scripture-prophecy</hi> did not Accomplish All Things to the very <hi>heighth,</hi> and it Self also, Both the <hi>Prpophccies</hi> that went before it, and it Self, would lose the due glory of Truth; for all the swelling <hi>Rhetorick</hi> and seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Hyperboles,</hi> either in describing <hi>Mercies</hi> or <hi>Judgmrnts,</hi> had but Party-fulfillings before, and look hither, to be perfectly fulfilled, that they may make good All, that was spoken heretofore to every <hi>lota</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Honour</hi> therefore of the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in all Considerations, it cannot be, but this Prophecy must draw a Line over the <hi>Christian Church,</hi> from the <hi>Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> to the End of All Things; And if it be, but granted, it Pourtrays the Last End, every Thing is so enterwoven, it must also give the Events before it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 2. Seeing God hath given such a <hi>New Testament-Prophecy,</hi> and there hath been in the Judgment of all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> so great a Defection from the Truth and Purity of Christianity, that hath spread so far, and born up so long, it cannot be suppos'd, but that so Great a <hi>Prophecy</hi> should give notice of it, that the Servants of Christ by some Crevices of Light at all Times, as it hath in every Age come to pass, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106748:17"/> by a Full, and Clear Light, e're the End, should know, that this Thing was Foretold before it came to pass, that when it comes to be Discover'd, and fully lay'd Open and Bare; There may be Adorings of the Infinite Wisdom, and Truth of God in Giving such a sure Word of <hi>Prophecy</hi> concerning it: Thus when the Barbarous Nations Rush'd in upon the <hi>Christian Empire,</hi> and its Ruin and End was Foreseen; There was a Stream of Light from this <hi>Propheey,</hi> that caus'd a General Sound in the Church at that Time, that <hi>Antichrist</hi> was Born; And it was so; He then according to this <hi>Prophecy</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd into his Succession; So about the Year 800, when <hi>Image Worship</hi> was establish'd, and so from Time to Time, till the <hi>Reformation,</hi> there have been Sneesings by a Power of God, as I may so express it, of this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and Light breaking forth, that the <hi>Papacy</hi> and <hi>Catholick Rome</hi> were <hi>Antichrist,</hi> the <hi>Whore of Babylon;</hi> and <hi>Popes</hi> the <hi>Beast,</hi> that Carried Her. So that it is even Prodigious, that, as Men speak, at this Time of Day, so near the Fall of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> Any of the Protestant Elders or Ministers, and, as I firmly Believe, of the Witnesses of Christ, should demur to this, whether the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> have describ'd the State of Papal <hi>Rome,</hi> or should once call it into doubt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 3. It were Prodigy, if so Great a <hi>New Testament Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> as the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> or <hi>Revelation</hi> should so magnifie the <hi>Roman Pagan Empire,</hi> becoming <hi>Christian,</hi> because of the Cessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Persecution, and the Grandieur of <hi>Temples, Monaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> the <hi>Christian Hierarchy,</hi> as to date so Glorified a <hi>Milenni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or 1000 <hi>Years</hi> upon it, as is set out, <hi>Rev. 20. 1, &amp;c.</hi> when at the same Door, that These Things came in, the Christian Purity, Humility, Mortification, Self-denial, Contempt of this World went out; and together with that Grandieur, came in Ambition, Avarice, Luxury, striving for Places, Dignities, Titles, in Regard of which, even the Christian Church hath been the <hi>Emporium,</hi> or Exchange for such Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique; and so, notwithstanding the Reformation, continues to this day, besides the Idolatry, Superstition, Fopperies of all Kinds, that have Crowded, yea, Rush'd in as a Mighty Flood; on which Account there hath been, one may say, a 1000 <hi>Years</hi> Fair for All those Wares of that Bill of Merchandise; <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 12, I say it might be call'd such a Milennial Fair, were it not that it hath continued so much above the 1000
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106748:18"/>
               <hi>Years,</hi> as to Grow now very near 1260. the <hi>Reformation</hi> it self suffering both in its Honour and Purity, by the Length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of the Time of this Great Market or Fair, and some Retailings from it; The Trade of which, whoever of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to spoil, were Slaughter'd, even by Thousands; So that in the <hi>City</hi> or <hi>False Church,</hi> where this Fair was kept, is Found the Blood of the Martyrs of Jesus.</p>
            <p>Shall we call this then the 1000 <hi>Years,</hi> in which, Judgment was Given to the Saints? Is this the 1000 <hi>Years Reign with Christ,</hi> and the <hi>Binding of Sathan to deceive the Nations no more,</hi> when <hi>Masses, Pardons, Indulgences, Purgatory Latine Services, Bodies, Souls of Men, Necks of Emperors</hi> have been in a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Trade for this Worlds Wealth and State, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the whole <hi>Mundus Muliebris</hi> of the Whore. For my Part, I separate, as mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h as possible may be from Persons, who do not Act, I am sure, out of Malice; but I Dread to Think, how Great an Injury this is to the Divine Spirit; and how near it comes in the Matter of it to a Blasphemy of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> to Interpret his so Celebrated 1000 <hi>Years</hi> in this manner? For to Attribute to God the Works of the Devil, is the Reverse, or as it were the other side of Attributing the Works of God to <hi>Belzebub;</hi> what then, is it to make the 1260 Years of the <hi>Apostasie</hi> the 1000 <hi>Years Kingdom of Christ!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Besides, Was not <hi>Mahomets</hi> Venome Enforc'd by the <hi>Saracens</hi> within 300 Years from <hi>Constantine;</hi> How Contradictious is this Opinion then to it self!</p>
            <p>The much Truer Oracle, then such an Interpretation of the 1000 Years, concerning the <hi>Christian Empire,</hi> and what Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, was that Voice; <hi>Poyson is this day diffus'd into the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Almost Incredible Numbers of the <hi>Waldenses</hi> or <hi>Vaudois,</hi> Slaughter'd for keeping the <hi>Commandments of God,</hi> and Hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Testimony of Jesus,</hi> One would Think, should Raise a Horror in Any Protestant Interpreter of the <hi>Thousand Years</hi> to Fix them so, that the time of that Slaughter should Fall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Them; And yet so it must be, if They lye from <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi>'s <hi>Christian Empire,</hi> to the Year 1300.</p>
            <p>It is indeed true, That the Change of the <hi>Empire</hi> from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi> to <hi>Christian</hi> was a Stupendious Acquist of the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> of the Power of the <hi>Word of his Testimony,</hi> and of the <hi>Martydom of his Saints;</hi> As it was Recorded in <hi>Heaven;</hi> and as such it is Celebrated, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12. 10. And it Remains there as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106748:18"/> a sure Pledge of that Great <hi>Milennial Kingdom,</hi> but as on Earth, And that we might not be deceiv'd in it, It is said, That the <hi>Church</hi> immediately upon it <hi>Fled into the Wilderness,</hi> and the <hi>Devil came down on the Inhabitants of the Earth,</hi> as a great Woe, and with great Rage, dashing the several Parts of his own <hi>Kingdom</hi> one against another, <hi>Barbarians</hi> and <hi>Mahometans</hi> against <hi>Antichristians;</hi> and by the <hi>Beast,</hi> the great <hi>Antichrist,</hi> under the Name of the <hi>Vicar of Christ, making War against the Saints and Martyrs of Jesus:</hi> And thus it hath come to pass, as is very well known.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 4. There being then so great Evidence, the Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Years are a Blessed and Happy State of the <hi>Church;</hi> which without a very horrible Imputation to the Truth, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness or Wisdom of the <hi>Divine Spirit,</hi> cannot be supposed to be already Come and Past; we may be most Assured, by the Pinning of One Thing into Another, so Evidently, so Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably, that the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> hath drawn a Line over All Time from the <hi>Resurrection</hi> to the <hi>Thousand Years Kingdom of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, <hi>I</hi> doubt not, were to be made out with great Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to every Judicious, Unprejudiced Person, that such a <hi>Concat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nated Line of Time</hi> is drawn by the <hi>Churches</hi> in Succession One to Another, and that they may be Parallell'd very Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently with the successive Events of the <hi>Sealed Book of Visions,</hi> as <hi>I</hi> have already in several Intimations, in the <hi>Reformation Reform'd,</hi> and other Tracts made known; but shall now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve what every One may easily Try, that to each <hi>Church</hi> there is a <hi>Promise</hi> made that cannot be Fulfill'd, but in the <hi>New Jerusalem;</hi> for in the Description of that, the place of each Promise is to be found even to the very Last of Sitting Down on the <hi>Throne of Christ;</hi> for the <hi>Throne of the Lamb</hi> is said to be in the <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> and when Christ will have long <hi>Sate on that Throne,</hi> (as the <hi>Father</hi> upon his <hi>Throne,</hi> before Christ <hi>Sate down on it,</hi>) the <hi>Laodicean Saints shall be caught up to Him to sit down with Him, and to Judge the Dead with Him,</hi> and so to be <hi>Deliver'd up with the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But further to Clear this, <hi>I</hi> have not Time now, and therefore shall observe, how the several Parts of the <hi>Sealed Book Prophecy</hi> are undoubtedly Linked, and in very brief. The <hi>Seals</hi> are Lock'd One to Another, in their being <hi>Seven</hi> and so following one upon another in their Events <hi>Opened;</hi> That the <hi>Trumpets</hi> follow on the <hi>Seals,</hi> is made plain by the <hi>Sealing</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:106748:19"/> of the Hundred forty four thousand in the <hi>Sixth Seal</hi> against the Danger of the Blasting Wind of the very <hi>First Trumpet hurting the Earth;</hi> and the Reference made in the <hi>first Woe Trumpet</hi> to that <hi>Sealing;</hi> It was <hi>Commanded the Locusts</hi> they should <hi>Hurt only the Men who had not the Name of God in their Foreheads.</hi> The close Connexion of the <hi>Scals</hi> and <hi>Trumpets,</hi> are further and fully Assur'd by the <hi>Angels,</hi> having the <hi>Seaven Trumpet given them,</hi> and making <hi>themselves ready</hi> to sound within the <hi>Seventh Seal.</hi> The <hi>seven Trumpets</hi> therefore being so Connext with the <hi>Seals,</hi> have their undoubted Sequence One upon Another. The <hi>Vision</hi> of <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. is Connext with the <hi>First Vision</hi> of the <hi>Book seal'd</hi> and gradually <hi>Open'd,</hi> by its being then <hi>held open</hi> in the <hi>Angel's Hand.</hi> The <hi>Vision</hi> of Chap. 11. is tied to the <hi>Sixth Trumpet</hi> by the Remark at the End of it, that the <hi>second Woe, viz.</hi> of that <hi>Sixth Trumpet</hi> was <hi>past,</hi> and the <hi>Third Woe coming quickly,</hi> and so the <hi>seventh Angel</hi> immediately <hi>Sounded;</hi> and the <hi>Vision of the Witnesses</hi> must Run so far Backward into the <hi>former Trumpets,</hi> as One thousand two hundred and sixty <hi>Days</hi> will carry Them; and that will be upon due Enquiry found to be to the <hi>First Trumpet.</hi> The <hi>Seventh Trumpet</hi> is also tied to the <hi>Vision</hi> of Chap. 10. by that pronunciation upon it there Found, that it was to Come; that when it was <hi>Come,</hi> it should <hi>Fintsh</hi> the whole <hi>Mystery;</hi> and so the Explanation of it shews, for it reaches even to the Time of the <hi>Dead being judged,</hi> of <hi>Reward</hi> given to the <hi>Servants of God, Small</hi> and <hi>Great;</hi> which is a further Demonstration that the <hi>Apolyptical Prophecy</hi> must Run its Course from the <hi>Resurrection</hi> to the very End of Things, even the <hi>Resurrection of Saints.</hi> The <hi>Vision</hi> Chap. 12. is tied to the <hi>Vision</hi> Chap. 11. by the Twelve hundred and six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Days</hi> Found in both; But so, that the <hi>Vision</hi> Chap. 12. must be so far before that Chap. 11. As the <hi>Woman appearing cloathed with the Sun, &amp;c. Bringing forth▪ the Manly Birth, &amp;c.</hi> was before her Actual <hi>Flight.</hi> The <hi>Vision</hi> Chap. 13. of the <hi>Beast,</hi> is tied to Chap. 11. by the <hi>Beast making War the Saints,</hi> in both <hi>Visions;</hi> to Cap. 12. By the <hi>Dragon giving his Throne, Power,</hi> and <hi>great Authority to the Beast;</hi> Chap, 14, is tied to Chap. 7. by the 144000. <hi>Sealed</hi> with the <hi>Father▪s Name on their Forehead,</hi> a State Ovant; but Reserving <hi>Seals on their Foreheads,</hi> Chap. 7. As also to Chap. 10. by the <hi>Thunders open'd,</hi> by that <hi>Mystery God had Preach'd by all the Prophets,</hi> Carried through the <hi>midst of Heaven,</hi> by the <hi>Angels preaching the Everlasting Gospel,</hi> It is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106748:19"/> tied to Chap. 11. by the Denunciation against the Great <hi>City</hi> and the <hi>Beast,</hi> and to the <hi>Seventh Trumpet</hi> by the <hi>Voice</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerning the <hi>Saints of God,</hi> that <hi>Died in the Lord;</hi> By the <hi>Harvest</hi> and the <hi>Vintage.</hi> The <hi>Vision</hi> of Chap 15. Chap. 16. are tied to Chap. 14. by the <hi>Vials</hi> being <hi>Filled out of the Wine-Press Trodden;</hi> by the often mentioning of the <hi>Beast.</hi> So run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning back up to Chap. 13. to Chap. 11, to Chap. 12. by the mention of the <hi>Dragon,</hi> Chap. 17 is tied to Chap 11. to Chap. 13. by both the <hi>Beast</hi> and the <hi>City,</hi> spoken of a like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, Chap. 18. is undoubtedly fast bound to Chap. 17. and so to whatever former <hi>Visions</hi> that Chap. 17. is joyn'd, and also to Chap. 16. as the <hi>Seventh Vial.</hi> by <hi>Great Babylon coming in Remembrance before God;</hi> Chap. 19. Adheres to Chap. 18. and so to Chap. 11. Chap. 16. By the <hi>City Babylon, coming in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance,</hi> on which, Chap. 19 follow the <hi>Halalujahs</hi> on that <hi>Great Judgment,</hi> Vers. 1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is tied to Chap. 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the <hi>Beast</hi> and <hi>false Prophet;</hi> called there <hi>the Other Beast.</hi> Again to Ch. 16. by the Preparation to, and Success of the <hi>Battel of Armaggedon,</hi> to Chap 14. by the <hi>Wine-press Trodden,</hi> by the Crown on the Head of him, to whom the <hi>Heavens open;</hi> even as the <hi>Lord of the Harvest</hi> coming, and all his <hi>Saints,</hi> as the <hi>Armies of Heaven</hi> with Him; Chap. 20, Chap 21, Chap. 22. to <hi>v.</hi> 6. are most Inhabitably joyned to One Another; and Chap. 20. to all that went before, by the mentions of the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> the <hi>Beast,</hi> and to Chap. 19. The <hi>Slain by the Sword of Christ's Mouth;</hi> and the <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog, whose Number is as the Sand of the Sea,</hi> are the same under differing Representati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Lastly; They are tied to the <hi>Visions of the Churches,</hi> by the same <hi>Promises</hi> that make up the same Priviledges of that <hi>New Jerusalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These and innumerable more Instances may be given, and each One much more Enlarged upon; By which it will Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that the Great <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Revelation</hi> is one entire Body, in a double Portraicture given; One is that of the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> Anorher is that of the <hi>Sealed Book opened,</hi> whose several Parts are so knit by Joynts and Sinews, and by the <hi>Symmetry</hi> of the whole, which begins at <hi>Christ's Resurrection</hi> when the Kingdom was the Right of Christ, and ends in the Glorious State of his Kingdom in full and peaceable Possession; that whoever Considers but the last Part, must needs Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it hath never yet been; except he be either grosly Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106748:20"/> Heynously prejudic'd, or Deplorably mad, There being no part that can be divuls'd One from Another, but All Lying Close in a Line; If <hi>Rome</hi> in any State, or Time be once meant, as All Interpreters, <hi>Protestants,</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pals,</hi> and some <hi>Papals</hi> even to the Last Allow, It must be meant always, in one State or another; Till it Come to be Burnt, Sunk, as a Milstone; and then the Glorious, and Happy State Ensue, which Happy State can be no other, then this Great <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> This is perfect <hi>Apocalyptical</hi> Demonstration.</p>
            <p>And if Any one would set Himself seriously to consider it; He should Find the Figures, and Types of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> even to Admiration, to be Fitted to, not the Retired, and Secret; but (as becomes <hi>Prophecy</hi>) to the most known, and undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble History of the State of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> from the very <hi>Resurrection,</hi> to this very Time, without any Haling, or Straining to bring Them to Agreement: Which <hi>Roman Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> or <hi>Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> if Scripture Harmony may be taken, is undoubtedly the Fourth, and there is no Fifth Kingdom, much less a Sixth of that▪ Kind, as the Reverend Opponent Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, any more then Five, or Six Mettals in the <hi>Image, Dan.</hi> 2. or more then <hi>Four Beasts, c.</hi> 7. But that which follows the <hi>Four Mettals</hi> and <hi>Beasts,</hi> (Interpretatively <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> For the word <hi>Monarchy</hi> I stand not upon) is so Great a <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> as never yet hath been; But it is never call'd the <hi>Fifth,</hi> nor ought to be so call'd, being of another King; any otherwise but as it Follows the <hi>Fourth;</hi> And because it hath not yet Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, the <hi>Fourth Kingdom</hi> must yet be standing according to <hi>Prophecy;</hi> and to shew the <hi>Roman</hi> the <hi>Fourth,</hi> It is most vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible still in the <hi>Papal Supremacy.</hi> All which, I cannot but Think, is to due Satisfaction, made out in that Treatise of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> Nor need these <hi>Kingdoms</hi> be so universal, as of the World; (Such only, Christs shall be) but Great, and Illustrious <hi>Kingdoms</hi> in the Eye of the World, of History, and of Chronology, and in a Line of Succession, as a <hi>Calendar of Time;</hi> to which End, They are also Given, and are as in Arrest of the Expectation of <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s <hi>Throne, c.</hi> 43. 7, till They shall Expire; Soon after which <hi>Vision,</hi> the <hi>Vision</hi> of the <hi>Four Kingdoms</hi> in the <hi>Dream of Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> the then Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering Mouarch, <hi>Intrepreted by Daniel,</hi> was Given; and just be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the End of the Captivity in <hi>Babylon, viz.</hi> the first year of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106748:20"/> the last King <hi>Belshazzar,</hi> whose Reign was very short, <hi>c</hi> 7. again Given in the <hi>Four Beasts,</hi> least, as I said, <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s <hi>Throne</hi> should be then expected, because of the Cessation of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity; and again, least the <hi>Temple-State</hi> should be Expected by that <hi>Decree of Cyrus</hi> to Build it, to be the Fulfilling of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi>'s <hi>Visional Temple;</hi> There is another <hi>Vision</hi> in <hi>Belshazzar's Teird,</hi> (and according to Scripture-Register his Last) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 2300 <hi>Evens, Morns,</hi> are Given, e're the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> would be Justified or Atton'd, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> also speaks, or as we Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate, <hi>Cleans'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And because the last of these <hi>Monarchies, viz.</hi> the <hi>Roman,</hi> would be the Longest; The <hi>New Testament History</hi> Remarks it continually; and the <hi>Prophecy</hi> from its <hi>Pagan,</hi> to its <hi>Christian,</hi> from its <hi>Christian</hi> to its <hi>Antichristian</hi> State, and during its <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian,</hi> to its utter Ruin depaints it, in an Agreement so Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, as never was in the World betwixt <hi>Emblem, Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphic,</hi> or Device, (so call'd) and the Thing Intended to be Represented, as between the Divine <hi>Apocalyptical Images,</hi> and <hi>History:</hi> As I presume to say, I have in several, published discourses made out, and too Long now to Recollect: And whether This can be so by the Mediation of either Chance, or Fancy, I Appeal to the Judicious Opposer, and even to all Mankind to decide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Point</hi> 3 I therefore pass to the Third Point propos'd, <hi>viz.</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of that Great Question; whether the <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> are to begin with, and to Remain to the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Eternity,</hi> or are proper to the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> to Begin, and to End with that <hi>Oeconomy.</hi> And as in Appendage to this Point, a short Scheme of the Doctrine of the <hi>Resurrection</hi> will be necessary; and to Free it from some Doubts, Rais'd by the Objector. And herein I lay down Three Assertions, of which I will only in Strictest short Give the Arguments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Assertion</hi> 1. That though I most Heartily Rejoyce in so much Agreement with my Reverend Adversary, as that the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> shall have a <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth;</hi> Yet under this Agreement, we herein exceedingly differ; That while He understands the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi>'s Eternal <hi>Fruition;</hi> I Assert, the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth</hi> are only proper to that <hi>Oeconomical Kingdom of Christ,</hi> that is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the 1000 <hi>Years,</hi> according as I have discours'd, even the <hi>Kingdom of the Great Son of Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:106748:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 1. The <hi>World to come of the second Adam</hi> is described, Psal. 8. Even the <hi>Kingdom of Jehovah,</hi> Adon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inu, <hi>our Lord and King;</hi> when he hath All under him, He must have <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, Sun and Moon, and Stars,</hi> however their Light may be drowned; the <hi>Moon ashamed,</hi> and the <hi>Sun confounded,</hi> when <hi>He Reigns before his Ancients in Glory;</hi> and all the Great Kings Captive, as in a Pit under Him, <hi>Isa.</hi> 23. 23. till they are <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sited,</hi> or <hi>loofed</hi> in <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> after many Days, but to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure so but a short Time: And an <hi>Earth</hi> Adorn'd with all its <hi>Creatures;</hi> So from the upper <hi>Regions</hi> must be Dislodg'd that <hi>Prince of the Power of the Air,</hi> those <hi>Spiritual wickednesses</hi> now in <hi>Heavenly places,</hi> and from the Lower Regions, <hi>Vanity, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi> the <hi>Curse,</hi> and that <hi>Enmity</hi> the <hi>Fruit of the Curse,</hi> and an <hi>Ʋniversal peace</hi> ensue. And all this is peculiar to the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> that is, <hi>to Christ our Lord;</hi> whose <hi>Name shall be Excellent in all the Earth;</hi> and so not proper to the <hi>Eteonal Word,</hi> though in our <hi>Nature,</hi> in his <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Eternity;</hi> when <hi>God is All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum</hi> 2. The <hi>Prophet Esay</hi> Declaring the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> at the same Time Declares a <hi>Kingdom of the New Jerusalem,</hi> Chap. 65. 17. and Chap. 66. 22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the end; He sets out the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and <hi>New Earth,</hi> in such. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, as cannot fit the <hi>State of Eternity,</hi> but such a <hi>Kingdom</hi> as <hi>I</hi> have now set out: And to shew it a <hi>State</hi> that hath never been yet, he Describes the <hi>Misery of the Wicked</hi> in the Visibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of it; <hi>They shall go forth and behold the Carkasses of them, &amp;c.</hi> Which Two Things laid together, <hi>viz.</hi> A <hi>State</hi> so much a <hi>State of Creation▪</hi> and yet such a <hi>View</hi> of the <hi>Misery of the Lost,</hi> Argue very pressingly to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> before spoken, and not the <hi>Kingdom of God All in All,</hi> when the <hi>Saints</hi> are so United to Him alone, and all the <hi>Lost</hi> in the <hi>Lake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 3. The Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> Promulges the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and <hi>the New Earth,</hi> together with <hi>the Day of Judgment,</hi> which hath been proved to be all at this <hi>Appearing Kingdom of Christ;</hi> And together with the mention of the <hi>Thousand Years,</hi> proved proper to that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and to that <hi>Day;</hi> we find Intimation of so many <hi>Thousand Years,</hi> as but <hi>so many Days</hi> as the World will have then passed (upon the matter, <hi>Six</hi>) leading us to that <hi>Sabbatical Thousand.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:106748:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 4. The Apostle <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> is most Express, That when <hi>He saw the New Jerusalem coming down from God, out of Heaven, He saw New Heavens,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth,</hi> and the <hi>Former passed away;</hi> the very word that the <hi>Apostle Peter</hi> used; and <hi>He that Sate on the Throme.</hi> said, <hi>Behold I Create All New.</hi> And These, as we shall see, were Peculiar to the <hi>Thousand Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in each of these Proofs <hi>I</hi> Rest not upon Them single, but as the Weight of Scripture in so many several <hi>Scriptures</hi> presses down mightily hereunto; And in the same manner <hi>I</hi> shall in what follows, Rest upon a Constellation of <hi>Scriptures</hi> shining out, and their Rays, as it were, Contracted in the Center of each Assertion, which Thing <hi>I</hi> desire should be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly taken notice of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Assert.</hi> 2. The <hi>New Heaven</hi> and the <hi>New Earth</hi> shall end with the <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>conomy</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> even as They began with it, and shall not continue to <hi>Etrrnity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 1. The <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>New Earth</hi> having been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be Proper and Peculiar to the <hi>Oeaonomy</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> when ever that ceases, They must of Course and in the Nature of the Thing cease also.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 2. The <hi>Apostle John</hi> tells us, At the <hi>Appearance of Him that Sate on the Chrystal Throne,</hi> Revel. 20 11. Settng his Face, as it were, to the Resigning up <hi>the Kingdom</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>the Father,</hi> the <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth Flew away,</hi> by an Efficacious Motion of Dissolution; <hi>I</hi> say, into the <hi>Divine Immensity,</hi> not as Parts of the <hi>Divine Being,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> acknowledge is <hi>Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible</hi> without all Parts; but which is so <hi>Infinite,</hi> that <hi>I</hi> Humbly <hi>Adore Him</hi> in the <hi>Mystery of Creation,</hi> as Individuating each Creature; so that it is not <hi>God</hi> but it <hi>Self,</hi> and so Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of <hi>Sin, Ʋnhappiness;</hi> and yet the <hi>Divine Being</hi> is so <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mense,</hi> that we <hi>Finite Creatures</hi> cannot understand how it is Possible there should be any Room, in regard of a <hi>Being</hi> Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>All</hi> even Imaginary Space, for (as we speak) <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> or for any Creature to be out of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; But herein <hi>I</hi> have no Sentiment but with Scripture, and all sound Reason, and Orthodox Theology; observing only, the <hi>Apostle▪</hi> does not say, That the <hi>Worlds were made of Nothing,</hi> but that <hi>Things that are seen, were not made of Things that do Appear,</hi> Heb. 1 si. 3. And that in <hi>Him we live, move, and have our beings:</hi> Now according to the manner of speaking, these Expressions lead
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106748:22"/> to, I Endeavour to speak; but utterly disbelieve an Eternal Matter or Spirit, except the One Eternal Spirit God, or any Eternal Creature; A double Conflagration, I also know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of, nor believe any such: These <hi>Heavens</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> that now are, I know from the Apostle <hi>Peter,</hi> are <hi>Reserv'd for Fire;</hi> Of the New: I Read, that They Fly away, even those of the 1000 <hi>Years;</hi> As the necessary Connexion, and Sequence of Things from the <hi>Beloved City,</hi> Rev. 20. 9. to the <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> flying away, <hi>v.</hi> 11. Evince, though the Apostle Reca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulates, <hi>c.</hi> 21. 1. and being more full concerning Them, speaks of Them after the mention of their <hi>Flying away,</hi> as <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated,</hi> according to usual Transposals of <hi>Scripture;</hi> and They so <hi>Flew away,</hi> that not only Themselves, but <hi>Their place,</hi> was <hi>no more Found;</hi> So that no other could Succeed, which Argues also, that they were the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth</hi> that were spoken of, and that they continue not to Eternity▪ and that no other can succeed them: Much to be observ'd!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 3. That Great Expression of the Apostle; That the <hi>Son shall Surrender up the Kingdom,</hi> and be Subject, and God be <hi>All in All,</hi> and those Expressions of that Great Prayer of Christ. <hi>John 17. 24, &amp;c. That they may be one,</hi> as <hi>We are One, &amp;c. That the Love,</hi> wherewith <hi>Thou hast Loved Me, may be in Them,</hi> and <hi>I in Them, that They may Behold my Glory, for Thou Loved'st me before the Foundation of the World,</hi> do so exceedingly sway with me; That though I am Far from any such Thoughts, as the <hi>Deification</hi> of the Saints, or that They are not proper Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual Persons in that Enjoyment; Yet I cannot think, but that All State since the Creation, is Free Oeconomy, or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the <hi>Family</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Known to <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> the <hi>Manifold Wisdom of God,</hi> and for the Preparing Them, till it Comes to this Union, wherein the Material <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> can, though never so New, never so Pure, be of no use; For Their Great use in <hi>Declaring the Glory of God,</hi> will be at an End; There will be no moment of Time to look off from Beholding the <hi>Glory of the Father</hi> in the Eternal Word, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying through his Humane Nature the <hi>Loue,</hi> and the <hi>Glory He had with the Father before the World began;</hi> Which Appears to me Absolutely to Discharge all Created Mirrors of <hi>Divine Glory,</hi> and that even the Humane Nature of Christ, shall not be the Object Saints look upon; but the <hi>Medium,</hi> or Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106748:22"/> of the <hi>Glory of the Father</hi> in the Eternal Word; For that is the Glory, Christ had with the <hi>Father before the World began.</hi> This is the best Explanation of <hi>God All in All,</hi> of which Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Christ in his Humane Nature is the Blessed, both Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance, and as united to the Divine Person, the Assurance and Security: Very Subordinate Mirrors, if so much, Saints may be to one Another of this Glory; But no Creatures of a Lower Degree, can be without Loss: For why should that be seen in the Reflex, that is so near in the Original to Saints in a State of union to it, and so the Sight Direct.</p>
            <p>Nor can there be any need of other Things, as by way of Divertisement, when the Enjoyment, the Divine Being had of it self from Eternity, is the Saints Enjoyment, an Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment always New, of Infinite Perfection, and so no need of Variety; For it self is All.</p>
            <p>The need there may seem to be of the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> or a <hi>New Earth,</hi> as Mansions for the Saints Ile Speak of in the next Argument.</p>
            <p>But here I would observe, as a full Explanation of <hi>Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> (of which I have, and shall still make use) the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between <hi>Oeconomy,</hi> and the <hi>Eternal State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Oeconomy</hi> is a Free, and Arbitrary Dispensation of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Family of Heaven and Earth</hi> in his Government of it, according to the <hi>Councel of his Will:</hi> The Eternal State is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to a Law so Essential to Divine Wisdom, and Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, that God cannot deny Himself in it, and so He is in it, the <hi>King Invisible</hi> (but as in Christ) <hi>Eternal, Immortal,</hi> the <hi>Only Wise God, to whom be Honour and Glory, for ever and ever, Amen. 1 Tim.</hi> 1. 17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An <hi>Oeconomy</hi> is for a Time, Time can Rise no higher then to Receive an <hi>Oeconomy;</hi> The highest <hi>Oeconomy</hi> Time Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, is in its <hi>Fullnese of Times, viz.</hi> of <hi>All Time, Ephes</hi> 1. 10. There can be nothing to Time beyond the <hi>Fullness of Times,</hi> but <hi>Eternity:</hi> When Time shall have had <hi>Fullness of Times, Eternity</hi> Follows.</p>
            <p n="3">3. An <hi>Oeconomy</hi> is the shewing to <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> the <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Wisdom of God,</hi> by way of Preparation; The Eternal State is Absolute Fullness, and Rest; To serve this End in the highest <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of Preparation, as <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Priests</hi> a 1000 <hi>Years</hi> is the <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> And it is to Christ and his Saints, more then his Coming to Mere Judgment, No Loss on one side,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106748:23"/> nor on the other, because it Issues into Eternity. It being then declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, that God hath Freely, and according to the <hi>Good pleasure of his Grace,</hi> Predestinated to a <hi>Conformity to the Image of the Son</hi> the Eternal Word in <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> the Eternal Law of that Conformity, is according to the Essential Law of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Glory in the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>King Eternal, &amp;c.</hi> That <hi>He</hi> should be <hi>All in All,</hi> as before Explain'd; And even <hi>highest Oeconomy,</hi> and so <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>New Earth</hi> cease in the <hi>Kingdom delivered up,</hi> as Scripture witnesses. For the <hi>Glory</hi> from <hi>Eternity,</hi> must be the <hi>Glory</hi> to <hi>Eternity.</hi> Whatever is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of this <hi>flies away;</hi> whatever is Contrary to it, is in the Opposite Eternal State (to us an unfathomable Depth as yet) the <hi>Lake of the Second Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Great Doctrine of <hi>God All in All,</hi> deriv'd from our Lord, <hi>John</hi> 17. and his Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 24, &amp;c.</hi> is so far from being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Fundamental Errour, that it is to Me the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The <hi>Supream</hi> Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 4. There shall be no use of the <hi>New Heoven</hi> and of the <hi>New Earth,</hi> as a Palace of Christ and of his Saints of the <hi>First Resurrection Above,</hi> or of the <hi>Living Remaining Saints Below;</hi> And therefore they shall <hi>fly away;</hi> For They Ascend up with Christ far above <hi>All Heavens,</hi> into the <hi>Glory He had with the Father befoee the World began,</hi> when there was no such <hi>Heaven,</hi> nor such <hi>Earth;</hi> And he hath prayed, <hi>Where He is, They may be also.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here for the strengthning this Argument, <hi>I</hi> would offer by way of Appendage some brief proposals concerning the <hi>State of the Resurrection,</hi> Explaining and freeing from Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction my former Discourses concerning it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rropos.</hi> 1. The <hi>Glorious Bodies of the Resurrection,</hi> both of <hi>Christ the first Fruits,</hi> and Exemplar, and of his <hi>Saints Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd to him,</hi> are Both <hi>Specific</hi> of the <hi>Humane Nature;</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuate,</hi> as we speak, or make most Distinct the <hi>Person of Christ</hi> in it, and of <hi>each Saint,</hi> and so according to utmost Scripture-Light, <hi>They continue for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propos.</hi> 2. The <hi>Resurrection</hi> is Absolutely Necessary to the Perfection of the <hi>Redemption,</hi> freeing the Body from the <hi>Curse upon Sin,</hi> viz. <hi>Death,</hi> and is therefore called <hi>the Redemption of our Bodies,</hi> and <hi>the Redemption of those</hi> who make up the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Purchase;</hi> As if Christ had not, so if his Saints Rise not, we were yet in our Sins</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:106748:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Propos.</hi> 3. The <hi>Resurrection</hi> hath this Peculiar in it for the <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> That it is for Appearance in Glory, even All the Low, Despised, Martyr'd Servants of Christ shall be seen in Glory, as the Wicked's Greatests here shall be seen in Contempt, Dishonour, and Misery. This is the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of that <hi>Magnificent Show,</hi> He who is the <hi>Absolute Potentate</hi> will give▪ There must be therefore <hi>Bodies of Glory</hi> to be seen in; when this <hi>Show</hi> shall be over, though the <hi>Glorious Bodies</hi> shall on the Account before nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, continue for ever; Yet as for the Happiness of Union, they are so Spiritualiz'd and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to that State of <hi>High Spirituality</hi> of <hi>God All in All;</hi> That what the <hi>Apostle</hi> said of his <hi>Visional Exaltation,</hi> He knew not, <hi>whether in, or out of the Body</hi> shall be much more so, when <hi>Saints are Ʋnited to God All in All,</hi> and Drinking in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of that State, the Body will be of smallest notice to <hi>Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propos.</hi> 4. That the Doctrine of the <hi>Resurrection</hi> hath a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Respect to the <hi>Saints Dead in Christ,</hi> who are to be <hi>Rais'd,</hi> and to the <hi>Saints Living and Remaining,</hi> who are to be <hi>Chang'd,</hi> is agreed; and so in the Main, however differing in Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, It is also plain, That the <hi>Dead</hi> are <hi>Rais'd,</hi> and the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chang'd</hi> in one and the same moment, at the <hi>Sound</hi> of one and the same <hi>Trumpet, I</hi> in this fully Agree; For the Force of that, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Apocalyptick Seventh Trumpet</hi> Lasts till the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom deliver'd up;</hi> But the Difference is, whether the <hi>Dead</hi> are <hi>Rais'd;</hi> the <hi>Living Chang'd</hi> and <hi>Caught up</hi> at the same Moment. This <hi>I</hi> deny, and Assert the <hi>Thousand Years</hi> come between the <hi>Raising</hi> and <hi>Changing,</hi> the first Acts, and being <hi>Caught up,</hi> the last Act of <hi>Christ's Kingdom,</hi> on these Reasons. 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 52. 1 Thes.</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reason</hi> 1. If the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Afterward,</hi> or <hi>Then,</hi> does no <hi>more,</hi> as the Case being Parallel, There is just Cause to think it does more; it unavoidably yet shews, there may be such a Space; Because it is used to signifie a Greater Space, <hi>xiz</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Rising,</hi> and his <hi>Saints Rising at his Coming;</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare 1 <hi>Thes. 4. 17. 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reas.</hi> 2. Because if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Apostle</hi> intended no more by the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Remaining,</hi> being <hi>Chang'd;</hi> then that Those who hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to be <hi>Alive</hi> at <hi>Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Coming,</hi> which is <hi>sudden,</hi> and as a <hi>Thief,</hi> should not stay to <hi>Die,</hi> but be <hi>Changed</hi> with a Change equal to <hi>Dying;</hi> and being <hi>Rais'd;</hi> it had not Requir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d such a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106748:24"/> Preface, <hi>Behold, I shew you a Mystery;</hi> The Case would be Plain, and no Mystery▪</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reas.</hi> 3. Especially, when we consider, if the <hi>Apostle 1 Thes.</hi> 4. 13. had discours'd the Case of the <hi>Dead in Christ</hi> with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the <hi>Resurrection,</hi> as it looks to the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity,</hi> and not to the <hi>Glorious Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Thousand Years</hi> before <hi>Eternity,</hi> he had more justly plac'd his Care on the Saints that shall be <hi>Found Alive</hi> at the <hi>Coming of Christ,</hi> that They might not Fear, they should be Forgotten at that Time, then on the <hi>Dead Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Because the <hi>Resurrection</hi> being so often call'd <hi>The Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Dead:</hi> The <hi>Dead in Christ</hi> stand much Fairer than the <hi>Living</hi> for the <hi>Resurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Because the <hi>Apostle</hi> calls the <hi>Doctrine of the Resurrection</hi> of the <hi>Dead,</hi> a <hi>Principle</hi> in the <hi>Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Doctrine of Christ, Heb.</hi> 6. 2. But he styles the <hi>Change of the Living</hi> who <hi>die not,</hi> a <hi>Mystery, 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 51.</p>
            <p>But a <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Glorious Appearance</hi> before that of <hi>Eternity,</hi> the <hi>Living Saints</hi> seem'd Fairest for, and the <hi>Dead</hi> more like to stay for their <hi>Glorious Appearance,</hi> till the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity,</hi> which might be a just Reason of <hi>Mourning as without Hope</hi> of <hi>that State,</hi> on account of <hi>Dying Saints;</hi> Hither therefore the <hi>Apostle's▪</hi> Consolatory Discourse bends it self, Guided by the <hi>All-knowing Spirit,</hi> who both knew that <hi>Thousand Years King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and that he would Reveal it by the <hi>Apostle John,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> may say <hi>Peter</hi> also; though <hi>Dividing</hi> to every one of his Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as he pleas'd, He made no mention of the <hi>Thousand Years</hi> by the <hi>Apostle Paul▪</hi> This much Assures, the <hi>Apostle</hi> was carried both on the <hi>Dying Saints Rais'd,</hi> and the <hi>Living Chang'd</hi> for that <hi>Glorious Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Thousand Years</hi> before the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propos.</hi> 5. The Security of the <hi>Rising,</hi> and also of the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Saints</hi> from the Great <hi>Conflagration,</hi> may be understood by <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Zoar,</hi> Secur'd from <hi>Sodoms Flames;</hi> by the <hi>Three Worthies</hi> in the <hi>Furnace;</hi> much more by the <hi>Apostle Peter's.</hi> saying Vers. 3. <hi>The Lord knoweth how to deliver the Godly,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 9. And lastly, By the Excellency of the <hi>Bodies,</hi> not only of the <hi>Resurrection,</hi> but of this <hi>Mysterious Change</hi> the <hi>Apostle</hi> speaks of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propos</hi> 6. It is to be readily Granted, that notwithstanding the Equality of the <hi>Love of Christ</hi> to all <hi>Saints,</hi> yet <hi>One Star dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106748:24"/> from another in Glory;</hi> And the State of the <hi>Saints Above</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, as Equal to the <hi>Angels,</hi> the State of the <hi>Saints</hi> Below; who, as <hi>Adam</hi> in <hi>Paradise, Marry</hi> and are <hi>Given in Marriage;</hi> but free from All the <hi>Imperfections of Marriage</hi> now, beyond all Comparison, for They came in by <hi>Sin</hi> and the <hi>Curse;</hi> But such a State became the <hi>Geat Redeemer</hi> to Restore, because Lost by Sin. But yet these differing States of <hi>Saints</hi> make but one <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> in the <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> Both being but the One <hi>World to come</hi> of the <hi>Second Adam</hi> whereof <hi>I</hi> speak.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propos.</hi> 7. The Possibility of <hi>Dying</hi> even upon <hi>Adam,</hi> was to have been Overcome and Removed by his Obedience. In this <hi>Adam</hi> Failed and Died; The <hi>Second Adam</hi> the <hi>Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit,</hi> The <hi>Lord from Heaven</hi> Overcame <hi>Death</hi> in this, by standing the <hi>Surety</hi> of his <hi>Living Saints,</hi> till They are <hi>Caught up,</hi> and <hi>cannot Die any more,</hi> as the <hi>Saints</hi> Risen Above cannot; Else <hi>Death</hi> were not <hi>subdued.</hi> The very Possibility of <hi>Dying</hi> is a <hi>Terror</hi> of the <hi>Great Enemy Death,</hi> and to be Subdued by Christ.</p>
            <p>Thus, As <hi>Adam</hi> from a <hi>Paradisiac</hi> Body degenerated to a <hi>Vile Body</hi> by Sin; and shall be Exalted to a Glorified Body by Christ; So the <hi>Saints Alive</hi> at <hi>Christ's Coming,</hi> shall be <hi>Chang'd</hi> to <hi>Paradisiac</hi> from <hi>Vile Bodies,</hi> and at Last be <hi>Caught</hi> up to <hi>Bodies</hi> of perfect Glory with Christ: In all which, there is Great Beauty of Redemption, and nothing strange, as the Objector supposes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propos.</hi> 8. The Words, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 4. 17. Concerning being <hi>Caught up,</hi> are as in a <hi>Mystery</hi> mysteriously plac'd: Lay Those [<hi>Together with Them</hi>] to the words to <hi>Meet the Lord,</hi> viz. in a <hi>Rendezvouz,</hi> or <hi>General As<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>embly,</hi> at the <hi>Delivering up of the Kingdom,</hi> and All will be plain; And it is Evident, as the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Implies a <hi>Rescue,</hi> and may be fairly Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to that Forenam'd <hi>Rescue</hi> from <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> and the <hi>Laodicean Lukewarmness;</hi> So it could not be <hi>Together with the Rising-Dead in Christ,</hi> that they are so <hi>caught up;</hi> for Christ <hi>Brings them with him,</hi> as the <hi>Apostle</hi> expresly says; So They are not <hi>caught up</hi> at all, therfore not <hi>Together</hi> with the <hi>Living Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propos. 9. I</hi> make no more than One <hi>Heaven</hi> or <hi>Hell,</hi> though Both are variously Modell'd: 1. In the State of <hi>Separate Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</hi> 2. In <hi>Spirits</hi> Re-invested with <hi>Bodies,</hi> and during the <hi>Kingdom of Christ. 3. In the Kingdom delivered up,</hi> and in the <hi>Lake.</hi> So Scripture Teaches; Yet to shew it is All One <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:106748:25"/> however call'd the <hi>First,</hi> and One <hi>Death,</hi> however call'd the <hi>Second,</hi> Each is Set alike; as in Great Letters, and made most Remarkable: <hi>This is the First Resurrection</hi> that hath no <hi>Second</hi> Counter-distinguish'd to it, but the <hi>Second Death. This is the Second Death</hi> that hath no <hi>First</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-distinguish▪d to it, but the <hi>First Resurrection;</hi> One of These Receives or Devours All Mankind as Principalls, or Participants; Each of These begin at the Beginning, and are Compleat at the End of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ.</hi> The First Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection begins in <hi>the Dead in Christ rising first,</hi> and <hi>the Living chang'd;</hi> but its not <hi>perfect</hi> till the <hi>changed Saints</hi> are <hi>caught up,</hi> and <hi>put on Ineorruption</hi> and <hi>Immortality,</hi> and Exalted to an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibility of <hi>Dying;</hi> Implying an Absolute Decree of God, and Effects of his Redemption concerning it; So our Lord speaks, <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 36. The <hi>Second Death</hi> begins in the <hi>Beast</hi> and <hi>false Prophet cast into the Lake;</hi> and the <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Small</hi> of the <hi>Wicked Slain with the Sword of Christ's Mouth;</hi> but is not Filled up, till <hi>Satan, the Dead and Death are cast into the Lake;</hi> Then <hi>the last Enemy Death</hi> is quite <hi>subdued:</hi> Then that <hi>Song</hi> is Sung, <hi>O Death, where is thy Sting? O Grave, where is thy Victory?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the more distinguishing Pillar of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> Begun, is the <hi>First Resurrection</hi> at his <hi>Coming.</hi> The more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguishing Pillar of the End of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> is the <hi>Second Death;</hi> For then the <hi>Kingdom of Christ is deliver'd up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Point</hi> 4. I come now to the Last Point, <hi>viz.</hi> of an Illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Restoration, or as the Apostle calls it, <hi>Reception, Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Full Orb'd Light of Israel;</hi> which very words well weigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, enforce that Great Truth to be Asserted; That there is to be such a <hi>Reception</hi> oppos'd to their <hi>Rejection,</hi> such a <hi>Reconciliation</hi> oppos'd to their being <hi>Enemies,</hi> such a Full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness oppos'd to their <hi>Diminution,</hi> that was not, when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle wrote nor should be, as all, he says, Implys, till the End: This being a General Perswasion of most Christians, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving such a Face of <hi>Prophecy</hi> in all the <hi>Old Testament,</hi> set to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, needs less Proof: But I will just present Six Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. as being <hi>New Testament Prophetical Doctrine,</hi> and Freest from possible Evasion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 1. The Apostle in that Chap. 11 speaks of a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Some Broken off,</hi> of <hi>Some Saved,</hi> and at last of a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Saved; The First enfolds the Generality in that State of Reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction Ever since; The Second Comprehends all the Saved,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106748:25"/> who whatever Numbers they may have been, are but <hi>Some,</hi> till it comes to <hi>All Israel sav'd; v. 17. v. 14. v.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 2. The <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>First Fruits</hi> being holy, the Spread Tree of Branches, and the whole Lump, must Appear in that State; The <hi>Love of God to Christ, God over All, Blessed for ever,</hi> who <hi>Came of Them;</hi> The <hi>Love of God to the Fathers,</hi> His <hi>Gifts,</hi> and <hi>Calling, without Repentance</hi> Require this; And it must not be in part, but in whole; The <hi>Saviour must come on Mount Zion,</hi> and turn <hi>Ʋngodliness from Jacob;</hi> when God according to his <hi>Covenant takes away your Sin, v 16. v.</hi> 27. 28. even their Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, their Self-cursing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 3. The <hi>Good Olive</hi> is their <hi>Own Olive, God is able, He will, How much more, Graft them in,</hi> then the <hi>Branches of the Wild Olive,</hi> and yet them he hath, and will still Graft in <hi>v.</hi> 23, 24. In this the Power of God is much Engag'd, <hi>Ezek 37. 9. He will Beat for them▪ One by One,</hi> Isa. 27. 12. <hi>Sift for them,</hi> Amos. 9. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum▪</hi> 4. The time is set for this, when the <hi>Gentile Churches</hi> come out of the Eclips of the <hi>Apostasie,</hi> to their <hi>Full Orb of Light,</hi> to their time of <hi>Full Mercy;</hi> when the time for the <hi>Riches</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> comes, for <hi>Life from the Dead viz.</hi> of the <hi>First Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> of the Saints in the <hi>New Heaven Above,</hi> and of the <hi>Living Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Saints</hi> in their happy Change in the <hi>New Earth</hi> beneath, till then Conversions are Rare: All this hath not yet been, <hi>v</hi> 22▪ 25. 12. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 5▪ As the <hi>Gentiles</hi> before Christ had a long time of <hi>Ʋnbelief,</hi> and of not <hi>Obtaining Mercy,</hi> from which they had a Rescue by Christ, so <hi>must the Jews have from their Ʋnbelief,</hi> and not <hi>Obtaining Mercy, v.</hi> 30, 31.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 6 This, both Doctrine and Providence, is a <hi>Mystery, Gentile Churches wise in their own Eyes</hi> Think there is no need of this Restoration of <hi>Israel,</hi> to their True Church Perfection: Such Excellent Persons, as the present Objector, may not see it, even because It is a <hi>Mystery, v.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>These Arguments well consider▪d, will Answer all the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Objections I am now dealing with, and shew, that as the <hi>Patriarks, Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Apostles, Saints</hi> of the <hi>First Resurrection,</hi> shall have a Glory, particular to them in the <hi>New Heaven</hi> above, so of their Posterity, there shall be <hi>Living Remaining Saints;</hi> who shall in that State be so different, Freed from any of those Perplexing Doubts Fitted only to this present Earth, as to Illustrate the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> State below.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:106748:26"/>
            <p>And thus I have with the high Esteem of the Person, I have this debate with, for his Excellent Works sake in general, in the Gospel, and with that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Verccundia,</hi> the Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, Sollemnity, Gravity, due to so Great a Subject, as the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> Endeavour'd to discourse it; And with that Brevity, I am on all Accounts necessitated unto, but yet am not Conscious, that I have Baulked any Material Objection of the worthy Adversary; but that what I have said, will meet with it, with all the Resolution, and Satisfaction I am Able to give; And so I cannot but hope, that neither on one side, or on the other, such debates ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sin, but that the Truth of God hereby will be made manifest; and by <hi>Running to and fro, Knowledge be Increas'd;</hi> And I still make humble Offers by Conference, or Entercourse of Writing, to give All Satisfaction I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n further; desiring only the Axe may be laid to the Roote, by shewing the Inconsistency of what I have Argu'd, with the Scriptures, from which I have Argued, or with any other Scriptures.</p>
            <p>In the mean, I profess with meekness, and due Awe, my Assurance of the Truth of my Prophetic Doctrine; I own I Look upon my self, as a <hi>Voice,</hi> as a Forerunner to the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Everlasting Gospel</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> now near at Hand; I humbly expect the dawn of the <hi>Morning Star</hi> upon the <hi>Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dois,</hi> and the <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>Witnesses of Christ</hi> yet in <hi>Sackcloth,</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> even the next <hi>Summer;</hi> and I cannot but hope, by the Service of our present Soveraign to the <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> And I do declare, had I not this hope in <hi>Scripture Prophecy,</hi> I were of <hi>All Men most Miserable.</hi> But <hi>Glory</hi> be to <hi>Free Grace,</hi> I shall not be <hi>Ashamed</hi> of my <hi>Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>